<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../tools/802_tei_odd/out/vicav_profiles.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="../tools/802_tei_odd/out/vicav_profiles.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="profile_{location}_01">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A machine-readable profile of Aleppo Arabic</title>
            <author>Claudia Laaber</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>ACDH-OeAW</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna</pubPlace>
            <date>2019</date>
            <availability status="restricted">
               <p>
                  <ref type="license"
                       target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/3.0/"/>
               </p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>This is an original digital text</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <tagsDecl partial="true">
            <rendition xml:id="i" scheme="css">font-style:italics;</rendition>
            <rendition xml:id="u" scheme="css">text-decoration:underline;</rendition>
            <rendition xml:id="b" scheme="css">font-weight:bold;</rendition>
         </tagsDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="zotID"
                       matchPattern="([a-z]+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://www.zotero.org/groups/2165756/vicav/items/itemKey/#$1">
               <p>Private URIs with the prefix "zotID" point to the respective bibliographic record in the VICAV Zotero library and/or to a local copy of it.</p>
            </prefixDef>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change status="created" when="2018-05-02T08:20:00Z" who="#">created</change>
         <change status="draft" when="2020-03-07T11:12:00Z" who="#">last modified (revision 1)</change>
         <change status="draft" when="2020-09-24T12:35:04.494+02:00">transformed to TEI-XML</change>
         <change when="2020-09-24T12:35:05.102+02:00" status="draft"/>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div>
            <head>
               <figure>
                  <graphic url="%E1%B8%A4alab/media/image1.jpeg"/>
                  <head type="imgCaption">Stephan Procházka 1988</head>
               </figure>
               <label>Name (English)</label>
               <name xml:lang="eng">Aleppo</name>
               <label>Name (Fuṣḥā, transcription)</label>
               <name xml:lang="ara">Ḥalab</name>
               <label>Name in local variety (in transcription)</label>
               <name xml:lang="ara-x-DMG">Ḥalab</name>
               <label>Name in local variety (in transcription)</label>
               <name xml:lang="ara-x-DMG">Ḥalab aš-šahbāʔ</name>
               <label>Name (Fuṣḥā, Arabic)</label>
               <name xml:lang="ajp">حلب</name>
            </head>
            <div type="positioning">
               <head>Geo location</head>
               <p>
                  <geo>36°12’ N 37° 9’ E</geo>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="typology">
               <head>Typology (Local)</head>
               <p rend="typology">East (Mashreq)&gt;Levant&gt;Syria&gt;North</p>
               <p>Urban sedentary dialect</p>
            </div>
            <div type="general">
               <head>General</head>
               <p xml:space="preserve">During the past few years, Aleppo has been notorious as one of the worst-hit regions of the persistent Syrian civil war, suffering devastation and an immense number of causalities and fatalities. </p>
               <p xml:space="preserve">The city has a long history. It is considered one of the oldest continuously inhabited urban centres in the world, being a settled site for over 5000 years.</p>
               <p xml:space="preserve">Because of its location at the western terminus of the Silk Road, Aleppo has always been an important trade centre. Under Ottoman rule it became the administrative capital of a province that included parts of Syria and Turkey, and was one of the strategic strongholds of the Ottoman Empire.</p>
               <p xml:space="preserve">After the First World War and the rather random drawing of new borders, Aleppo’s trade ties with important surrounding cities got weaker. However, its manufacturing sector survived and flourished an the city became a thriving industrial centre rivalling Syria’s capital Damascus.</p>
               <p xml:space="preserve">Aleppo is especially famous for its olive oil soap, which is, despite the difficulties of war, still being produced. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="researchHistory">
               <head>Research history</head>
               <p xml:space="preserve">Sabuni (1980) is a comprehensive description of the phonology and morphology of Aleppo’s Arabic and includes a few texts at the end. </p>
               <p xml:space="preserve">Bar-Moshe and Arnold (2017) is a comparative study of the Jewish dialects of Aleppo and Baghdad, specifying numerous shared linguistic features and comparing the two dialects to others in the region. </p>
               <p xml:space="preserve">Nevo (1991) wrote his PhD thesis on the phonology and morphology of Arabic-speaking Jews of Aleppo. </p>
               <p xml:space="preserve">Behnstedt (1987) is a study about the elative forms of words with quadrilateral roots.</p>
               <p xml:space="preserve">Levin (2002) dealt with the imāla in Aleppine Arabic. </p>
               <p xml:space="preserve">Jastrow &amp; Kazzarah (1980) is the text (including notes on special features) of a then 80-year-old speaker talking about his memories of his youth during Ottoman rule. Jastrow &amp; Kazzarah (1984) contains texts from different speakers, translated into German with notes. Behnstedt (1989) focuses on the Christian variety of Aleppine Arabic and includes texts with German translations: this study also provides information about the classification of the varieties spoken in the city and describes the different phonological and morphological features of the Christians’ dialect. Behnstedt (2000) offers texts of both Muslim and Christian Aleppine Arabic.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="dictionaries">
               <head>Dictionaries</head>
               <p xml:space="preserve">Barthélemy‘s (1935-1954) is a monumental dictionary mainly based on the dialect of Aleppo.</p>
               <p xml:space="preserve">A list of dictionaries for Syrian Arabic, which might be useful for Aleppo as well, is provided <ref target="https://vicav.acdh.oeaw.ac.at/">here</ref>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="textBooks">
               <head>Text books</head>
               <p xml:space="preserve">There is no textbook focusing on Aleppine Arabic in particular. However, the Damascene vernacular is definitely helpful for communicating with Aleppine speakers. A comprehensive two-volume textbook containing numerous texts and exercised is Aldoukhi et al. (2014). A list of other textbooks for Syrian Arabic can be found <ref target="https://vicav.acdh.oeaw.ac.at/">here</ref>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="bibliography">
               <head>Bibliography</head>
               <p xml:space="preserve">{leave empty}</p>
            </div>
            <div type="sampleText">
               <head>Sample text</head>
               <p xml:space="preserve">{leave empty}</p>
            </div>
            <div type="lingFeatures">
               <head>Linguistic features</head>
               <p xml:space="preserve">{leave empty}</p>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>