<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="profile_urfa_01">
    <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
          <title>A machine-readable language profile of Urfa Arabic</title>
          <author>Stephan Procházka</author>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
          <publisher>ACDH-OeAW</publisher>
          <pubPlace>Vienna</pubPlace>
          <date>2011</date>
          <availability status="restricted">
            <p>
              <ref type="license" target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/3.0/"/>
            </p>
          </availability>
        </publicationStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
          <p>This is an original digital text</p>
        </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
      <body>
        <div>
          <head>
              <figure>
                  <graphic url="320px_urfaskyline2.jpg"/>
              </figure>
            <name xml:lang="eng">Şanlıurfa</name>
            <name xml:lang="ara">الرها</name>
            <name xml:lang="ara-x-DMG">ar-Ruhā (no longer in use)</name>
            <name xml:lang="arz-Latn" type="latLoc">urfa ~ al-midīne</name>
          </head>
          <div type="positioning">
            <p>
              <geo>37.15, 38.79</geo>
            </p>
          </div>

          <div type="typology">
            <p>Arabia › Northern Group › Syro-Mesopotamian fringe</p>
            <p>Bedouin dialect, minority variety</p>
          </div>

          <div type="general">
            <p>Because the official language of the region is Turkish, the
              Arabic dialect of the city of Urfa is a minority language. Similar
              varieties of Arabic are spoken in many villages and smaller towns
              (e.g. Harran and Akçakale) situated between Urfa and the Syrian
              border. Urfa Arabic is linguistically very close to the dialects
              of the sheep and goat breeding nomads (the so-called Shawāya) of
              the Syrian Steppe and arguably constitutes the northernmost
              variety of the Arabian Bedouin dialects. Tribal structures among
              the local Arabic speakers (estimated to be around 150,000) are
              still very strong, and the relatively strict endogamy results in a
              high proportion of first language speakers even among the youngest
              generation. Urfa Arabic is usually not written; but there are
              internet sites containing phrases, songs, and proverbs in
              vernacular Arabic written in Latin script.</p>
          </div>

          <div type="researchHistory">
            <p>Although the existence of Arabic speaking groups in the region
              has been known since at least the 19th century, the dialect is
              still poorly documented. A very short grammatical sketch is 
              <ref target="bibl:prochazka_ferrando_2003_0001">Procházka
              2003</ref>, three texts with English translation are found in
              Procházka 2013, and a comparison of Urfa Arabic with other
              peripheral dialects of the region is 
              <ref target="bibl:prochazka_2006_0000">Procházka 2006</ref>.</p>
          </div>

          <div type="sampleText">
              <p>VICAV provides a <ref target="sample:urfa_sample_01/Şanlıurfa">Sample Text </ref> of this variety. </p>
          </div>

        </div>
      </body>
    </text>
  </TEI>