<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="profile_douz_01">
    <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
          <title>A machine-readable language profile of Douz Arabic</title>
          <author>Veronika Ritt-Benmimoun</author>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
          <publisher>ACDH-OeAW</publisher>
          <pubPlace>Vienna</pubPlace>
          <date>2011</date>
          <availability status="restricted">
            <p>
              <ref type="license" target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/3.0/"/>
            </p>
          </availability>
        </publicationStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
          <p>This is an original digital text</p>
        </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
      <body>
        <div>
          <head>
            <figure>
                <graphic url="Tunisia_10_12_064_Douz_and_the_Festival_of_the_Sahara_6609290791.jpg"/>
                <head type="imgCaption">Source: <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Douz#/media/File:Tunisia_10-12_-_064_-_Douz_and_the_Festival_of_the_Sahara_(6609290791).jpg">Wikimedia</ref>
              </head>
            </figure>
            <name xml:lang="eng">Douz</name>
            <name xml:lang="ara">دوز</name>
            <name xml:lang="ara-x-DMG">Dūz</name>
            <ref target="#xpath1(//author)"/>
          </head>
          <div type="positioning">
            <p>
              <geo>33.45, 9.01</geo>
            </p>
          </div>

          <div type="typology">
            <p>Western › Maghreb › Tunisia › Southern Tunisia</p>
            <p>Bedouin type dialect, Sulaym group</p>
          </div>

          <div type="general">
            <p>The town of Douz is one of the greatest oases in the so-called
              Nifzāwa region situated south-east of the Šaṭṭ al-Ǧarīd (Chott
              el-Jerid). Its dialect is more or less identical to the speech of
              the formerly semi-nomadic Maṛāzīg tribe which numbers around
              30,000 members. The Marzūgī dialect is an archaic variety of
              Maghrebinian Bedouin Arabic and exhibits features such as gender
              distinction with plural forms and internal passive voice (although
              of restricted use) with verbs. As a Bedouin dialect it is
              considered a low-variety by the speakers of sedentary dialects,
              e.g. of the capital Tunis, but highly appreciated by the Bedouins
              themselves. Only some young speakers show the tendency to
              accommodate to urban sedentary speech. With its rich lexicon it is
              the vehicle for popular poetry. As a representative of the Sulaym
              Group of Maghrebi Bedouin dialects it is widely understood in
              Libya and Eastern Algeria.</p>
          </div>
            
          <div type="researchHistory">
            <p>The only detailed grammatical description of the dialect of Douz
              is Ritt-Benmimoun's <ref target="bibl:ritt_benmimoun_2014_0000">Grammatik des arabischen Beduinendialekts der Region Douz
                (Südtunesien)</ref>. For many decades the research done by
              Gilbert Boris was the only reliable source for the Marzūgī
              dialect. Nearly all his main works were published after his death
              (<ref target="bibl:boris_1951_0001">Boris 1951a</ref>, 
              <ref target="bibl:boris_1951_0000">Boris 1951b</ref>, 
              <ref target="bibl:boris_1958_0000">Boris 1958</ref>). Starting in
              the early 2000s, Veronika Ritt-Benmimoun has begun to publish a
              great number of articles dedicated to the language and culture of
              the Maṛāzīg (see below). A voluminous monograph which includes
              many ethnographical texts in the dialects of the Maṛāzīg and other
              Bedouin tribes of the region is <ref target="bibl:ritt_benmimoun_2011_0001">Ritt-Benmimoun 2011
                (554 pp.)</ref>. Hitherto, the Marzūgī dialect is the only
              Tunisian Bedouin dialect for which rich linguistic data is
              available.</p>
          </div>
            
          <div type="bibliography">
            <p>To see a list of relevant publications in our database 
               <ref target="bibl:geo:Douz">click here</ref>.</p>
          </div>
            
          <div type="dictionaries">
            <p>
              <ref target="bibl:boris_1958_0000">Boris 1958</ref> is a very
              good and quite comprehensive Arabic-French dictionary (686 pp.).
              Additional data is found in <ref target="bibl:bin_murad_1999_0000">Bin Murād 1999</ref>.</p>
          </div>
            
          <div type="audioData">
            <p>22 recordings found on the Semitic Sound Archiv. Follow 
            <ref target="http://www.semarch.uni-hd.de/index.php43?LD_ID=16&amp;RG_ID=47&amp;ORT_ID=144&amp;lang=de">this link</ref>.</p>
          </div>
        </div>
      </body>
    </text>
  </TEI>