<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="profile_ahwaz_01">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>A machine-readable profile of Ahwaz/Ahvaz Arabic</title>
                <author>Bettina Leitner</author>
                <editor xml:id="charly" role="Technical_Editor">Karlheinz Moerth</editor>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>ACDH-OeAW</publisher>
                <pubPlace>Vienna</pubPlace>
                <date>2018</date>
                <availability status="restricted">
                    <p>
                        <ref type="license" target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/3.0/"/>
                    </p>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>This is an original digital text</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change who="#charly" when="2018-10-03" status="released"/>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    
    <text>
        <body>
            <div>
                <head>
                    <figure>
                        <graphic url="ahwaz_300px_pol_sefid_27.jpg"/>
                        <head type="imgCaption">Source: <ref target="https://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/commons/9/9b/Pol_Sefid_27.JPG">Wikimedia</ref>
                        </head>
                    </figure>
                    <name xml:lang="eng">Ahwaz/Ahvaz</name>
                    <name xml:lang="ara">al-Ahwāz</name>
                    <name xml:lang="ara-x-DMG">al-Aḥwāz</name>
                    <name xml:lang="ajp">الأهواز</name>
                </head>
                <div type="positioning">
                    <p>
                        <geo>31.31, 48.68</geo>
                    </p>
                </div>
                <div type="typology">
                    <p>East › Mesopotamia › Iraq › South Iraq</p>
                    <p>Bedouin-type gələt dialect; mixed variety with urban and rural features; strong Persian influence on the lexicon</p>
                </div>
                <div type="general">
                    <p>Ahwāz is the capital city of the southwestern Iranian province of Khūzestān and situated alongside the river Kārūn. Of its 1.5 million inhabitants Arabs are 
                        the largest  ethnic group, the second biggest group are Persians. There is also a small group of Sabeans living in Aḥwāz. </p>
                    
                    <p>The city was apparently flourishing in pre-Islamic times but declined in the subsequent centuries to a village of about 10,000 
                        inhabitants in the early 20th century. </p>
                    <p>Today many of the city’s inhabitants are working in the sugar cane and oil industry. </p>
                    <p>With the discovery of oil in the vicinity of Aḥwāz (1908) and during the time of the Iran-Iraq war, in which Aḥwāz was considered one of province’s the safer cities, many Arab
                        people from the surrounding areas have moved to the capital city. This resulted in the penetration of many rural features into the originally urban dialect of Aḥwāz and thus
                        reshaped its linguistic profile. </p>
                </div>
                <div type="researchHistory">
                    <p>The first written document on the dialect of Aḥwāz is an unpublished and undated manuscript by D. Lorimer, in which he collected mainly lexical lists and verbal conjugation
                        patterns. Further linguistic information on the dialect of Aḥwāz and other villages and cities in Khūzestān was gathered by Bruce Ingham, who published two articles (<ref
                            target="bibl:ingham_1973_0000">1973</ref>, 1976) on regional differences within Khūzestān including short texts, and a short grammatical analysis in EALL (2007). <ref
                            target="bibl:ingham_1991_3237">Ingham (1991)</ref> is a short study on sentence structure in Khuzestan Arabic. </p>
                </div>
                <div type="bibliography">
                    <p>To view a list of the important publications on Iranian Arabic <ref target="bibl:reg:Iran">follow this link</ref>.</p>
                </div>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
