<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="profile_baghdad_01">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>A machine-readable language profile of Baghdad Arabic</title>
                <author>Stephan Procházka</author>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>ACDH-OeAW</publisher>
                <pubPlace>Vienna</pubPlace>
                <date>2011</date>
                <availability status="restricted">
                    <p>
                        <ref type="license" target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/3.0/"/>
                    </p>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>This is an original digital text</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change who="#stephan" when="2018-10-03" status="released"/>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>

    <text>
        <body>
            <div>
                <head>
                    <figure>
                        <graphic url="320px_Haifa_street_as_seen_from_the_medical_city_hospital_across_the_tigres.jpg"/>
                        <head type="imgCaption">Source: <ref target="https://commons.wikimedia.org/wiki/File:Haifa_street,_as_seen_from_the_medical_city_hospital_across_the_tigres.jpg">Wikimedia</ref>
                        </head>
                    </figure>
                    <name xml:lang="eng">Baghdad</name>
                    <name xml:lang="ara">بغداد</name>
                    <name xml:lang="ara-x-DMG">Baġdād</name>
                </head>

                <div type="positioning">
                    <p>
                        <geo>33.33, 44.38</geo>
                    </p>
                </div>

                <div type="typology">
                    <p>Eastern › Mesopotamian › Iraqi gǝlǝt (gilit)</p>
                    <p>Urban Bedouin dialect with significant sedentary substrate, high-prestige variety</p>
                </div>

                <div type="researchHistory">
                    <p>The dialect of the Iraqi capital can be regarded as the prestige variety of the whole country. It is frequently used in the media and widely understood not only in Iraq, but
                        also in the adjacent Gulf region, in Eastern Syria, and in the Iranian province of Khuzestan. The linguistic setting of Baghdad is special for its so-called “communal
                        dialects”. The current prestige variety (described here) is actually the dialect which until fairly recently was spoken solely by the Muslim population. The Christian and
                        Jewish (no longer in Iraq) inhabitants of Baghdad speak a very different dialect of the so-called <hi rend="italic">qǝltu</hi> type, which is much closer to Northern Iraq and
                        not influenced by Bedouin features.</p>
                    <p>The first comprehensive descriptions of the Arabic dialect of Baghdad did not appear before the 1960s. Before that only some very brief remarks (Jeannier 1888, Massignon 1912)
                        and a few textbooks and glossaries were published, particularly Van Ess 1917 (second edition 1938, many <ref target="bibl:van_ess_0000">reprints</ref> until 1989) and van
                        Wagoner 1949, but both contain a mixture of various Iraqi dialects and cannot be regarded as dialectological descriptions. The first scholarly monographs published were <ref
                            target="bibl:malaika_1963">Malaika 1963</ref> and <ref target="bibl:erwin_1963_0001">Erwin 1963</ref>, shortly followed by <ref target="bibl:blanc_1964_0001">Blanc
                            1964</ref>. Blanc, who coined the term “communal dialects”, presented a rather concise but excellent description of Muslim, Christian, and Jewish Baghdadi. <ref
                            target="bibl:abu_haidar_1991_0001">Abu-Haider 1991 </ref> deals with the Christian variety. <ref target="bibl:palva_2009_001">Palva 2009</ref> convincingly argues that the
                        Bedouin (= gǝlǝt type) character of present-day Muslim Baghdadi is mainly the result of a process of bedouinization during the past 300 years. Thus, for a considerable time
                        after the Mongol sack of Baghdad in 1258, the dialect of Baghdad had remained to be an urban Mesopotamian type dialect that has only slowly changed due to immigration from the
                        countryside. In spite of its importance, Baghdad Arabic has not been intensively studied (compared to, e.g., Cairo or Damascus) and almost all reference works date back to the
                        1960s.</p>
                </div>

                <div type="bibliography">
                    <p>Our database contains <ref target="bibl:geo:Baghdad">a number of publications </ref> that deal with Baghdad. To get a wider picture look for <ref target="bibl:reg:Iraq"
                            >reg:Iraq</ref>.</p>
                </div>

                <div type="sampleText">
                    <p>VICAV provides a <ref target="sample:baghdad_sample_01/Baghdad">Sample Text of Baghdad </ref> of Baghdad Arabic. </p>
                </div>

                <div type="lingFeatures">
                    <p>There is also a <ref target="feature:ling_features_baghdad/Baghdad">list of linguistic features</ref> with example sentences.</p>
                </div>

            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
