<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="profile_soukhne_01">
    <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
          <title>A machine-readable profile of Soukhne / Al-Sukhnah
            Arabic</title>
          <author>Julia Baumgartner</author>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
          <publisher>ACDH-OeAW</publisher>
          <pubPlace>Vienna</pubPlace>
          <date>2018</date>
          <availability status="restricted">
            <p>
              <ref type="license" target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/3.0/"/>
            </p>
          </availability>
        </publicationStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
          <p>This is an original digital text</p>
        </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
      <body>
        <div>
          <head>
            <name xml:lang="eng">Soukhne / Al-Sukhnah</name>
            <name xml:lang="ara">as-Suxna</name>
            <name xml:lang="ara-x-DMG">Suxni</name>
            <name xml:lang="ajp">السخنة</name>
          </head>
          <div type="positioning">
            <p>
              <geo>34.88, 38.87</geo>
            </p>
          </div>
          <div type="typology">
            <p>East (Mashriq) › Levant › Syria &gt; Oases and Steppe
              Dialects</p>
            <p>Sedentary dialect with many influences of the surrounding
              bedouin-type dialects</p>
          </div>
          <div type="general">
            <p>Soukhne is a town located in the Syrian Steppe close to the
              eastern border of the province of Homs. The importance of the
              former caravan city increased throughout the centuries, when the
              town developed into a trade centre. Trade took place mostly
              between Bedouin tribes, for example the tribal confederation of
              ˁAnaza, and the local merchants. The town severely suffered from
              the civil war in Syria, particularly between 2015 and 2017 when it
              was under control of ISIS forces.</p>
            <p>Soukhne is described as a town with a dynamic history. Local
              merchants used to travel to various Syrian regions, but also to
              Iraq and Turkey and therefore adopted different linguistic
              elements that contributed to the shaping of the dialect of
              Soukhne. <ref target="bibl:behnstedt_1994_0001">Behnstedt
                1994</ref> describes the dialect as a mixture of bedouin and
              sedentary elements.</p>
          </div>
          <div type="researchHistory">
            <p>The first description of the dialect of this oasis is found in
                <ref target="bibl:cantineau_1956_0000">Cantineau 1956</ref>.
              The most comprehensive study on the dialect spoken in Soukhne is
              undoubtedly <ref target="bibl:behnstedt_1994_0001">Behnstedt
                1994</ref>. Consisting of three parts, this work includes a
              broad variety of ethnographic texts in Part 1 as well as an
              in-depth investigation of phonology, morphology and syntax in Part
              2. </p>
          </div>
          <div type="dictionaries">
            <p>A comprehensive glossary is found in <ref target="bibl:behnstedt_1994_0001">Behnstedt 1994</ref>, Part
              3. It is based on the texts of Part 1 of the same book.</p>
          </div>
          <div type="textBooks">
            <p/>
          </div>
          <div type="audioData">
            <p>There are 113 audio-files of texts from Soukhne in SemArch -
              Semitisches Tonarchiv: <ref target="http://www.semarch.uni-hd.de">http://www.semarch.uni-hd.de</ref>
            </p>
          </div>
          <div type="bibliography">
            <p>To view a list of the important publications on this variety 
                <ref target="bibl:geo:Al-Sukhna">follow this link</ref>.</p>
          </div>
        </div>
      </body>
    </text>
  </TEI>