<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
     xmlns:w="http://schemas.openxmlformats.org/wordprocessingml/2006/main"
     xmlns:r="http://schemas.openxmlformats.org/officeDocument/2006/relationships"
     xmlns:rl="http://schemas.openxmlformats.org/package/2006/relationships"
     xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
     xml:id="profile_qameshli_01">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A machine-readable profile of Qamishli Arabic</title>
            <author>Maria El Fadel</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>ACDH-OeAW</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna</pubPlace>
            <date>2018</date>
            <availability status="restricted">
               <p>
                  <ref type="license"
                       target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/3.0/"/>
               </p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>This is an original digital text</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div>
            <p>PPP:file:/C:/Users/KMoerth/ch_data/git/vicav_content/contributions/vicav_profiles_qameshli__001.docx_xslt_cascade</p>
            <head>
               <name xml:lang="eng">Qamishli</name>
               <name xml:lang="ara">al-Qāmišlī</name>
               <name xml:lang="ara-x-DMG">Qāməšli</name>
               <name xml:lang="ajp">القامشلي</name>
            </head>
            <div type="positioning">
               <p>
                  <geo>37.05, 41.22</geo>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="typology">
               <p>East (Mashriq) › Mesopotamia › Anatolia</p>
               <p>Mixed dialect with many features of Anatolian qəltu-type sedentary dialects</p>
            </div>
            <div type="general">
               <p>Qamishli is a large town in north-eastern Syria, bordering on the Turkish city of Nusaybin. Officially established in 1926 as a station on the Baghdad Railway, the city grew rapidly and became an important transport hub and the economic and cultural centre of the region. Qamishli is characterized by its ethnical, cultural and religious diversity. The population consists of Armenians, Assyrian Christians, Kurds and Arabs. The migration background of the town’s population contributed to the dialect that is spoken in this city nowadays.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="researchHistory">
               <p>Due to the very recent history of the town it does not possess a peculiar dialect. However, many speakers who have been living there for a longer time speak a so-called non-autochthonous qǝltu-dialect which originates from Anatolia, particularly Mardin. Lahdo 1999 contains three texts, Lahdo 2000 a short grammatical analysis. Sketches of the phonology and morphology of similar dialects of the region are found in Behnstedt 1992.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="dictionaries">
               <p>In Lahdo 1999 a five-page glossary is found.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="textBooks"/>
            <div type="audioData"/>
            <div type="bibliography"/>
            <div type="sampleText"/>
            <div type="lingFeatures"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
