<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:space="preserve" xml:id="profile_nablus_01">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      
        <titleStmt>
            
        <title>A machine-readable profile of Nablus Arabic</title>
        
        <respStmt>
            <name xml:id="gunda">Gunda Kinzl</name>
            <resp>author</resp>
        </respStmt>
    
      
            <respStmt>
                <resp>data management and conversion</resp>
                <name xml:id="DS">Daniel Schopper</name>
            </respStmt>
        </titleStmt>
    
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>ACDH-OeAW</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Vienna</pubPlace>
        <date>2021</date>
        <availability status="restricted">
          <p>
            <ref type="license" target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/3.0/"/>
          </p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>This is an original digital text</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <tagsDecl partial="true">
        <rendition xml:id="i" scheme="css">font-style:italics;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="u" scheme="css">text-decoration:underline;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="b" scheme="css">font-weight:bold;</rendition>
      </tagsDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    
<revisionDesc><change who="#DS" when="2025-04-14" type="minor">adding @type on tei:graphic (add_type_to_graphic.xsl)</change><change who="#DS" when="2025-08-28" type="minor">refactoring author and editor elements to respStmt (author2respStmt.xsl)</change></revisionDesc></teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div>
        <head>
          <figure>
                  <graphic url="nablus_wikimedia.jpg" type="thumbnail"/>
                  <head type="imgCaption" xml:space="preserve">
                        <ref target="https://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/commons/thumb/3/3e/Nablus_12.jpg/640px-Nablus_12.jpg">Wikimedia</ref>
                        </head>
               </figure>
          <label>Name (English)</label>
          <name type="place" xml:lang="eng">Nablus</name>
          <label>MSA name</label>
          <name xml:lang="ara">نابلس</name>
          <label>MSA name (trans.)</label>
          <name xml:lang="ara-x-DMG">Nāblus, Nābulus</name>
          <label>Local name (trans.)</label>
          <name xml:lang="ajp-Latn" type="latLoc">Nābləs</name>
        </head>

        <div type="positioning">
               <head>Geo location</head>
          <p>
              <geo>32°13'N 35°15'E</geo>
              <country>Israel, Palestine</country>
            </p>
        </div>

        <div type="typology">
          <p>East (Mashreq) &gt; Levant &gt; Palestine &gt; Central Palestine</p>
          <p>urban variety</p>
        </div>

        <div type="general">
          <p>Nablus lies in a fertile valley between Mount Gerizim (Ǧabal aṭ-Ṭūr) and Mount Ebal 
              (Ǧabal ˁAybāl). It was founded under the Roman emperor Vespasian in 72 CE and named 
              Flavia Neapolis. The name “Nablus” is a corrupted form of “Neapolis”. In Hebrew, it 
              is called Shechem, because of an erroneous association of Nablus with the ancient 
              Canaanite city of this name.</p>
          
          <p>It is one of the biggest cities in the West Bank and a centre of commerce and culture. 
              It used to rely on agricultural production from its hinterlands, particularly olive oil, 
              from which it famously produced soap. It was the main city of a relatively autonomous 
              area and a centre of resistance to the British Mandate authorities and the Israeli 
              occupation, respectively. Due to the role it played in both intifadas, it was largely cut 
              off from the surrounding villages by checkpoints, thus impeding trade and hindering 
              economic development. Nablus is often referred to as Ǧabal an-Nār, the “mountain of fire”. 
              This is understood to be a reference to its rebelliousness.</p>
            
            <p>Mount Gerizim is the religious centre of a Samaritan minority. Although their religious 
                belief is a branch of Judaism, the political affiliation of Nablus’ Samaritans is mostly
                with the West Bank Arabs, but they strive to keep a neutral position in the conflict. 
                There are also Samaritans who live in Holon, near Tel Aviv. The Samaritans have their 
                own distinct dialect and do not intermarry with the rest of Nablus’ population, but 
                sometimes with the Jewish population of Israel.</p>
        
        <p>Historically, trade relations in the region ran East-West in the wider area, and Nablus 
            shares close familial relations (and linguistic ties) with as-Salt and Amman, 
            as attested by <rs type="bibl" ref="zotid:CBZND4FV">Al-Wer 2007</rs>.</p>
        
        </div>

        <div type="researchHistory">
         <p>Several bits and pieces of information about the dialect of Nablus seem to be common 
             knowledge among Palestinians, and it is described in several sources as being 
             distinctively different from other dialects.</p>
            
         <p><rs type="bibl" ref="zotid:GJ9VKTBU">Bauer 1926</rs> (first published 1898) provides general information 
             on Palestinian Arabic. <rs type="bibl" ref="zotid:S2N4A7KD">Bergsträsser 1915</rs> provides some 
             information on Nablus, but that old Arabic <hi rendition="#i">q</hi> and <hi rendition="#i">k</hi> 
             should have merged into k as described by Bergsträsser is contested by 
             <rs type="bibl" ref="zotid:IJ3WK87I">Arnold 2013</rs>, who believes this account indicates an unreliable source 
             for Bergsträsser’s data. Arnold himself heavily relies on the master’s thesis by 
             <rs type="bibl" ref="zotid:ZJLGDDIP">Annuri 1979</rs> in his comparative description of the Samaritan and Muslim majority dialect 
             of Nablus, for which he only conducted fieldwork on the former. Other characteristic 
             features Arnold describes are a strong final imāla <hi rendition="#i">ā</hi> &gt; <hi rendition="#i">e</hi> and the personal pronoun 
             1st pers. sing. <hi rendition="#i">ʾani</hi>.</p>
         <p><rs type="bibl" ref="zotid:BB6AAG8K">Abdel Jawad 1987</rs> holds that people who use the voiceless uvular 
             plosive [<hi rendition="#i">q</hi>] as a reflex of standard [<hi rendition="#i">q</hi>] are commonly marked as “Nabulsi”, 
             as this is a feature that used to distinguish it from other urban Levantine dialects. 
             However, [<hi rendition="#i">q</hi>] tends to be abandoned by younger generations in favour of 
             the glottal stop [<hi rendition="#i">ʔ</hi>], and seems to have disappeared almost entirely, save 
             for the speech of older and uneducated speakers who use [<hi rendition="#i">q</hi>] categorically. 
             As <rs type="bibl" ref="zotid:BB6AAG8K">Abdel-Jawad 1987</rs> notes, this is despite the fact that Nablus 
             is a regional centre and could function as a reference point for a regional prestigious 
             variety. The thesis of the [<hi rendition="#i">q</hi>] reflex of [<hi rendition="#i">q</hi>] is in accordance with Arnold.</p>

            <p>Apart from that, Nablus shows a strong Damascene influence not only 
                culturally – it is often called “Little Damascus” – but also linguistically. This is 
                especially true for the Samaritan minority.</p>
            
            <p>Even though Nabulsi is apparently such a characteristic dialect, comprehensive descriptions 
                do not exist, apart from <rs type="bibl" ref="zotid:ZJLGDDIP">Annuri’s unpublished master’s thesis</rs>. The Samaritan 
                dialect, however, is described by <rs type="bibl" ref="zotid:8Q3WEDYA">Stenhouse 1989</rs> and characterized by 
                a strong final imāla. <rs type="bibl" ref="zotid:HMMF39HQ">Arnold 2006</rs>, whose source is an older Samaritan 
                woman who grew up in Holon and has lived in Nablus for some time, also 
                provides texts and a description, in addition to <rs type="bibl" ref="zotid:6DUEL9IZ">Arnold 2003</rs> dealing 
                exclusively with the Samaritans of Holon. The aforementioned work by 
                <rs type="bibl" ref="zotid:IJ3WK87I">Arnold 2013</rs> deals with the Samaritan dialect, but also mentions 
                characteristics of the general Nablus dialect.</p>

            <p>The dialect of Nablus has played an important role in the formation of more 
                recently developed dialects, namely that of Amman, as attested by <rs type="bibl" ref="zotid:CVGWJHTQ">Herin 2019</rs>. </p>
        </div>

        
        <div type="bibliography">
               <p>To view publications on this variety click <rs type="bibl" ref="bibl:geo:Nablus">here</rs>.</p>
            </div>
               </div>

    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
