<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="../xsl/tei_2_html__v006.xsl"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="profile_amman_01">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A machine-readable profile of Amman Arabic</title>
            <author>Claudia Laaber</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>ACDH-OeAW</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna</pubPlace>
            <date>2019</date>
            <availability status="restricted">
               <p>
                  <ref type="license" target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/3.0/"/>
               </p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>This is an original digital text</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <tagsDecl partial="true">
            <rendition xml:id="i" scheme="css">font-style:italics;</rendition>
            <rendition xml:id="u" scheme="css">text-decoration:underline;</rendition>
            <rendition xml:id="b" scheme="css">font-weight:bold;</rendition>
         </tagsDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change status="created" when="2018-05-02T08:20:00Z" who="#">created</change>
         <change status="draft" when="2020-04-08T12:34:00Z" who="#">last modified (revision 1)</change>
         <change status="draft" when="2020-09-24T09:36:21.035+02:00">transformed to TEI-XML</change>
         <change when="2020-09-24T09:36:21.967+02:00" status="draft"/>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div>
            <head>
               <figure>
                  <graphic url="amman_sp__2017.jpg"/>
                  <head type="imgCaption">Courtesy of Stephan Procházka, 2017</head>
               </figure>

               <label>Name (English)</label>
               <name type="geo" xml:lang="eng">Amman</name>
               <label>Name (Fuṣḥā, transcription)</label>
               <name xml:lang="ara">ʕAmmān</name>
               <label>Name in local variety (in transcription)</label>
               <name xml:lang="ara-x-DMG">ʕAmmān</name>
               <label>Name (Fuṣḥā, Arabic)</label>
               <name xml:lang="ajp">عمّان</name>
            </head>
            <div type="positioning">
               <head>Geo location</head>
               <p>
                  <geo>31°57′N 35°56′E</geo>
<country></country>
               </p>
            </div>

            <div type="typology">
               <p rend="typology">East (Mashreq)&gt;Levant&gt;Jordan&gt;North</p>
               <p>Mixed type dialect</p>
            </div>
            <div type="general">
               <p>Jordanian dialects have been a widely neglected area in the field of Arabic dialectology.</p>
               <p>The linguistic situation is due to the city’s and countries history a
               very special one and cannot be investigated without taking a closer look at it.
               Before Amman was announced the capital of Jordan in 1921, it was a
               rather small and unimportant village inhabited by 5000 Circassian migrants,
               who settled there because they were forced to leave their homeland in the cause of the Russo-Circassian war.</p>

               <p>The city experienced fast growth as many Jordanians left their villages
                  and moved to the capital. Additionally, many Palestinian and Syrian merchant families settled in Amman. </p>
               <p>As there was nothing like a real native Arab population of Amman, they were all using the dialects of their hometowns. </p>
               <p>Also, Amman experienced influxes of refugees from other Arab countries:</p>
               <p>During the Arab-Israeli war in 1948 and the six-days war in 1967 many
                  Palestinian refugees arrived in Amman. Because of the Gulf war in 1991
                  and the invasion of Iraq in 2003 many Iraqis and Kuwaitis settled in the
                  city. The recent migration wave started with the Syrian Civil war in 2011.</p>

               <p>Young people in Amman started calling themselves <hi rendition="#i">ʕammāniyīn</hi> (inhabitants of Amman) –
               a word that has not been in use before indicating that this generation is
               the first one feeling native to the city and starting to create Amman’s koine. </p>
               <p>Research has shown that Jordanian dialects and urban Palestinian dialects are the most influential ones in the process of koineization. </p>
            </div>

            <div type="researchHistory">
               <p>As the koine is still evolving, there is no detailed grammar of Amman Arabic existing right now.</p>
               <p>Al-Wer (2011, EALL) is a concise linguistic sketch giving an overview
               about the most common features. Sawaie (EALL) provides further information
               on the history of Jordan, its linguistic situation as well as a short sketch of important research. </p>

               <p>Most of the research until now has a major focus on the dialect’s phonology:</p>
               <p><rs type="bibl" ref="zotid:L8X448R5">Al-Wer (2002)</rs> is dealing with the
               first generation considering themselves as native Ammanis (<hi rendition="#i">ʕammāniyīn</hi>) and the set of consonants and vowels they are using in their speech.</p>
               <p><rs type="bibl" ref="zotid:">Al-Wer (2003)</rs> is a study on the
               pronunciation of the 2nd person plural pronominal suffix. It
               is a diachronic study as she is pointing out the development of its pronunciation in three successive generations of Amman.</p>
               <p>A further article of Al-Wer (2007) can be seen as a summary of
               the two previous topics. In her introduction she is giving concise
               information on the dialect situation of Amman in an interwoven manner
               with the city’s history. The article therefore is a good way to get a first insight on the linguistic situation in Amman.</p>
               <p><rs type="bibl" ref="zotid:SMK2SIMI">Abdel-Jawad (1986)</rs> examines
               the emergence of urban dialects in Amman and Irbid providing
               sociophonetic information. His PhD thesis is an investigation on
               lexical and phonological variation in Amman. (The full text is available <ref target="https://search.proquest.com/docview/303188711">here</ref>.)</p>

               <p><rs type="bibl" ref="zotid:X7EEJJAC">Zawaydeh (1998)</rs> as well
               as <rs type="bibl" ref="zotid:GK7CAGI4">Zawaydeh and de Jong (2011)</rs> focus on the phenomena of uvularization in Ammani Arabic.</p>

               <p>Heselwood and al-Tamimi have undertaken two phonetic studies:
               The first is dealing with laryngeal and pharyngeal consonants <rs type="bibl" ref="zotid:2S94J7B9">(2011)</rs> and
               the second with plain and emphatic coronals <rs type="bibl" ref="zotid:DEESKNVR">(2011)</rs>.</p>

               <p><rs type="bibl" ref="zotid:QT3T2V7U">Prokosch (1991)</rs> lists
               Ottoman Turkish loanwords in Ammani Arabic. <rs type="bibl" ref="zotid:FM963KF5">Zibin
               and Al-Tkhayneh (2019)</rs> is a sociolinguistic analysis of the use
               of English loanwords inflected with Arabic morphemes – features that are mostly used by young people as a slang language. </p>
            </div>

            <div type="bibliography">
               <p>For a list of publications concerning Arabic in
                  Jordan click <rs ref="bibl:reg:Jordan">here</rs>, for Palestine click <rs ref="bibl:reg:Palestine">here</rs></p>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
