<?xml version="1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="profile_jisr_azZarqa_01">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>A machine-readable profile of Jisr az-Zarqa Arabic</title>
                <author xml:id="gunda">Gunda Kinzl</author>
                <editor xml:id="charly" role="Technical_Editor">Karlheinz Moerth</editor>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>ACDH-OeAW</publisher>
                <pubPlace>Vienna</pubPlace>
                <date>2021</date>
                <availability status="restricted">
                    <p>
                        <ref type="license" target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/3.0/"/>
                    </p>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>This is an original digital text</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <tagsDecl partial="true">
                <rendition xml:id="i" scheme="css">font-style:italics;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="u" scheme="css">text-decoration:underline;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="b" scheme="css">font-weight:bold;</rendition>
            </tagsDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
        
</teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div>
                <head>
                    <figure>
                        <graphic url="jisr_azzarqa_wikimedia.jpg"/>
                        <head type="imgCaption"><ref target="https://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/commons/thumb/4/48/Jisr_az-Zarqa.jpg/640px-Jisr_az-Zarqa.jpg">Wikimedia</ref>
                        </head>
                
                    </figure>
                    <label>Name (English)</label>
                    <name type="place" xml:lang="eng">Jisr az-Zarqa</name>
                    <label>MSA name</label>
                    <name xml:lang="ara">جسر الزرقء</name>
                    <label>MSA name (trans.)</label>
                    <name xml:lang="ara-x-DMG">Ǧisr az-Zarqāʾ</name>
                    <label>Local name (trans.)</label>
                    <name xml:lang="ajp-x-DMG" type="latLoc">Ǧisir, Ǧisir iz-Zarga</name>
                </head>
                <div type="positioning">
                    <head>Geo location</head>
                    <p xml:space="preserve">
                        <geo>32°32'N 34°54'E</geo>
                        <country>Israel, Palestine</country>
                    </p>
                </div>
                <div type="typology">
                    <p xml:space="preserve">East (Mashreq) &gt; Levant &gt; Palestine &gt; Central Palestine</p>
                    <p xml:space="preserve">Carmel Coast dialect with Bedouin influences</p>
                </div>
                <div type="general">
                    <p xml:space="preserve">Ǧisir iz-Zarga is the only town in Israel on the Mediterranean coast with 
                        an exclusively Arab populace. It gets its name from the Wadi az-Zarqa/Taninim river.</p>
                    <p xml:space="preserve">The people of Ǧisir belong to three or four main tribes who each have their 
                        own oral history of ancestry. At least two different dialects are spoken according to Jastrow, 
                        confirmed by Behnstedt and Geva-Kleinberger. The <hi rendition="#i">ˁAmmāš</hi> and <hi rendition="#i">Ǧurbān</hi> 
                        claim that they came to Ǧisir from the Jordan Valley (<hi rendition="#i">ġōr</hi>). Indeed, a tribe or tribal 
                        confederation called the <hi rendition="#i">Ġawārna</hi> (sing. <hi rendition="#i">Ġōrānī</hi>) is found along 
                        the river Jordan and in the Galilee, and allegedly they settled also in <hi rendition="#i">li-Mqēble</hi> 
                        and Ǧisir. On the other hand, a geographical depression or swamp is called <hi rendition="#i">ġōr</hi>, typically a less 
                        desired portion of land, and historically often riddled with Malaria. Thus, the term may regardless 
                        of ancestry have been employed in a derogatory manner to denote the “people of the swamps”. Some 
                        outsiders even referred to the people of Ǧisir as <hi rendition="#i">ġaǧar</hi>, “gypsies”. They are described as particularly 
                        dark-skinned.</p>
                    <p xml:space="preserve">The <hi rendition="#i">Šihāb</hi> and <hi rendition="#i">Naǧǧār</hi> tribes possibly came to Ǧisir from Egypt or the Sudan, 
                        although the <hi rendition="#i">Naǧǧār</hi> claim Maghrebinian ancestry according to Jastrow. Geva-Kleinberger in personal 
                        correspondence states that they came to historic Palestine from Upper Egypt with Napoleon 
                        Bonaparte’s army in the early 19th century.</p>
                    <p xml:space="preserve">Their alleged collaboration with Israel in the first Arab-Israeli war in 1948 
                        has allowed Ǧisir’s citizens to stay in their village when most other villages in the area were 
                        destroyed, save for two others (<hi rendition="#i">Fradīs</hi> and <hi rendition="#i">Mifǧar</hi>, the latter later replaced by a power station). 
                        They were indispensable as workers and had helped drain the swamps in the coastal area as they were 
                        more resilient to Malaria.</p>
                    <p xml:space="preserve">Ǧisir az-Zarqa is a very poor town, crowded due to several factors preventing 
                        its expansion: The sea to the west, the Haifa-Tel Aviv road to the east, a natural reserve and the 
                        kibbutz Ma'agan Michael to the north and a dirt wall that separates it from the affluent Cesarea 
                        neighbourhood, built to keep out the sound of the muezzin and of celebrations on one hand and 
                        burglars from Ǧisir iz-Zarga on the other.</p>
                    <p xml:space="preserve">Opportunities are limited for the inhabitants of Ǧisir, half of which are below 
                        the age of 19, although there are some hopeful initiatives in place to revive the area as a tourist 
                        destination.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="researchHistory">
                    <p xml:space="preserve">There are several mentions of the dialect of the <hi rendition="#i">Ġawārna</hi>, but these studies 
                        deal with widely different areas. It remains unclear to what extent the <hi rendition="#i">Ġawārna</hi> had or still have 
                        a common dialect. For information on the <hi rendition="#i">Ġawārna</hi>, see <rs type="bibl" ref="zotid:S2N4A7KD">Bergsträßer 1915</rs> and <rs type="bibl" ref="zotid:5VSJEDQ8">El-Kayed Bani Yasin’s 1980</rs> 
                        doctoral thesis. <rs type="bibl" ref="zotid:3BLAD6MI">Rosenhouse 1984a</rs> and <rs type="bibl" ref="zotid:JJRQAHT4">1984b</rs> are a good overview of the Bedouin dialects in northern 
                        Israel mentioning the <hi rendition="#i">Ġawārna</hi> and also contain extralinguistic information.</p>
                    <p xml:space="preserve">Most importantly, <rs type="bibl" ref="zotid:2FQQFXLX">Jastrow 2009</rs> deals with Ǧisir. He distinguishes between a Ǧisir I 
                        and Ǧisir II dialect and places them within the group of “Carmel Coast dialects”, distinct from the 
                        dialects of the <hi rendition="#i">Muṯallaṯ</hi>.</p>
                    <p xml:space="preserve"><rs type="bibl" ref="zotid:U3NWLS6N">Behnstedt and Geva-Kleinberger</rs> in their excellent <hi rendition="#i">Atlas of the Arabic dialects of 
                        Galilee (Israel)</hi> take over Jastrow’s classification. It contains Jastrow’s material as well as own 
                        data on both Ǧisir I and II.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="bibliography">
                    <p xml:space="preserve">To view publications on this variety click <rs type="bibl" ref="bibl:geo:Jisr az-Zarqa">here</rs>.</p>
                </div>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>