<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:space="preserve" xml:id="profile_yemenite_jewish_arabic_01">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         
        <titleStmt>
            
            <title>A machine-readable profile of Yemenite Jewish Arabic</title>
            
        <respStmt>
            <persName xml:id="gunda">Gunda Kinzl</persName>
            <resp>author</resp>
        </respStmt>
    
         
            <respStmt>
                <resp>data management and conversion</resp>
                <persName xml:id="DS">Daniel Schopper</persName>
            </respStmt>
        </titleStmt>
    
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>ACDH-OeAW</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna</pubPlace>
            <date>2021</date>
            <availability status="restricted">
               <p>
                  <ref type="license" target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/3.0/"/>
               </p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>This is an original digital text</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <tagsDecl partial="true">
            <rendition xml:id="i" scheme="css">font-style:italics;</rendition>
            <rendition xml:id="u" scheme="css">text-decoration:underline;</rendition>
            <rendition xml:id="b" scheme="css">font-weight:bold;</rendition>
         </tagsDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      
<revisionDesc><change who="#DS" when="2025-04-14" type="minor">adding @type on tei:graphic (add_type_to_graphic.xsl)</change><change who="#DS" when="2025-08-28" type="minor">refactoring author and editor elements to respStmt (author2respStmt.xsl)</change><change who="#DS" when="2025-09-02+02:00" type="minor">renaming respStmt/name to respStmt/persName as expected of profile_1.xsl</change></revisionDesc></teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div>
            <head>
               <figure>
                  <graphic url="yemen_gisi_1990.jpg" type="thumbnail"/>
                  <head type="imgCaption">Courtesy of Gisela Procházka-Eisl, 1990</head>
               </figure>

               <label>Name (English)</label>
               <name type="place" xml:lang="eng">Yemenite Jewish Arabic</name>
               <label>Name (Fuṣḥā, transcription)</label>
               <name xml:lang="ara">al-lahǧa al-yahūdiyya al-yamaniyya</name>
                <label>Name (Fuṣḥā, Arabic)</label>
               <name xml:lang="ajp">اللهجة اليهودية اليمنية</name>
            </head>
            <div type="positioning">
                <head>Geo location</head>
                              <p>
                  <geo>15°30'N 47°30'E</geo>
                  <country>Yemen</country>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="typology">
               <head>Typology (Local)</head>
               <p rend="typology">East (Mashreq) &gt; Arabia &gt; Yemen</p>
                <p>The Jewish dialects of Yemen were similar to Muslim ethnolects in the countryside, whereas 
                    in the cities, there were distinct Jewish ethnolects. Many speakers are L1 Hebrew speakers today.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="general">
               <head>General</head>
               <p>Yemeni Jews today live in Israel, the USA, and elsewhere in the world. Only between 
                   100-300 still remained in Yemen in the early 2000s, according to estimates, and 
                   there are virtually none today.</p>
               <p>Yemeni immigration to what today is Israel began in the 1880ies. This was religiously 
                   and economically motivated and facilitated by the ability to travel freely within the 
                   Ottoman Empire. At that time, the Yemeni Jews were an organic part of Yemeni society.</p>
               <p>During the British mandate of Palestine, immigration certificates were given out only in 
                   limited numbers by the British authorities. When the atrocities of the Holocaust became 
                   known, the Zionist entity in secret operations sought to bring Jews from all over the 
                   world to Palestine to increase the Jewish presence. However, after the end of the 
                   Second World War, Holocaust survivors were prioritised in receiving immigration 
                   certificates and Yemeni immigration halted.</p>
               <p>The numbers of people waiting under dire conditions in camps in and around Aden, 
                   then a British protectorate, overwhelmed the British authorities. They tried to 
                   encourage the people to stay in Yemen, especially since many of them did not have 
                   the wealth or vocational training required to make a living unassisted by welfare 
                   measures.</p>
               <p>After the foundation of the state of Israel in 1948, the limitations on Jewish immigration 
                   fell.  By then, the Jewish community in Yemen had come under pressure as their formerly 
                   good relations with their Muslim neighbours deteriorated, and about 80 of them had 
                   been killed in a massacre in 1947 in Aden. Almost 50,000 Yemeni Jews were brought to 
                   Israel on planes in what was dubbed “Operation on Wings of Eagles” or “Operation Magic 
                   Carpet”.</p>
               <p>Yemeni Jews did not undergo secularisation before coming to Israel. To this day they 
                   are sometimes faced with orientalist views. For a long time, they were largely excluded
                   from positions of leadership, and they are generally still poorer than Ashkenazi Jews. 
                   Recognition for their culture and approval of their language, however, has increased 
                   in recent years.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="researchHistory">
               <head>Research history</head>
               <p>The vernacular of Yemenite Jews has been studied exclusively in Yemenite communities 
                   in Israel. Naturally, the dialects differ from each other as Yemen has a diverse 
                   dialect landscape. There were significant Jewish populations in cities such as Sanʿa 
                   and Saʿda as well as in rural tribal areas.</p>
               <p>Interest in the Yemenite Jews has been great, especially on the part of Israeli Jewish scholars. 
                   The view on them has been somewhat ambivalent: The Yemenis were seen as the preservers 
                   of an original and pure “Jewishness”, but also as “oriental” and “backward”.</p>
               <p>Two volumes published by <rs type="bibl" ref="zotid:CV88A289">Goitein in 1932</rs> and 
                   <rs type="bibl" ref="zotid:4WPGGK4Q">1934</rs> (in German) on Yemeni folk tales are among the earliest 
                   studies undertaken in Israel. <rs type="bibl" ref="zotid:37A862IU">Goitein 1960</rs> studied the 
                   language of the al-Gades village in lower Yemen. A valuable contribution to the knowledge 
                   of lexicon and popular proverbs and sayings is <rs type="bibl" ref="zotid:H3Q68AK6">Goitein 1970</rs>.</p>
               <p><rs type="bibl" ref="zotid:SPGEW23P">Diem 1973</rs> describes Jewish and other Yemenite dialects.
                    <rs type="bibl" ref="zotid:XEZAEM3H">Piamenta’s dictionary of 1991-1992</rs> in two volumes reflects both 
                   Judeo-Yemeni characteristics and other Yemeni colloquials. </p>
            <p>Studies undertaken in Hebrew on Yemenite Arabic are <rs type="bibl" ref="zotid:HM66CI5V">Kara 1986</rs>
                <rs type="bibl" ref="zotid:66QDS6FC">and Tobi 1986</rs>, among others.</p>
            <p><rs type="bibl" ref="zotid:TNGZJPKT">Shachmon’s 2007</rs> PhD dissertation (in Hebrew) as well as several 
                articles such as <rs type="bibl" ref="zotid:6KWTRZHW">Shachmon 2015</rs>, <rs type="bibl" ref="zotid:QLSM8PHP">2017</rs> and <rs type="bibl" ref="zotid:5PK94NJN">2020</rs>
                investigate the Yemeni Jewish vernacular.</p>
            <p><rs type="bibl" ref="zotid:PQXAMTU4">Geva-Kleinberger 2016</rs> is an article on the wedding songs of a community 
                from Ḥabbān in eastern Yemen that has preserved unique traditions. It also provides the 
                lyrics of the songs in transcription.</p>
            <p>Since 1989, the Tema: Journal for Judeo-Yemenite Studies is published in Hebrew.</p>
            <p>There have been ample studies of the Hebrew and Aramaic components in the speech of Yemenite 
                Jews, see for example <rs type="bibl" ref="zotid:Q9KXDYP3">Goitein 1931</rs> (in Hebrew), <rs type="bibl" ref="zotid:TQTZC6TB">Morag 2002</rs> and 
                <rs type="bibl" ref="zotid:JU5GTGDJ">Shachmon 2013</rs>. There are also many works on Judeo-Yemeni songs 
                and poetry, see for example <rs type="bibl" ref="zotid:6LMIV7YJ">Wagner 2008</rs>.</p>
            </div>

            <div type="dictionaries">
               <head>Dictionaries</head>
               <p>A dictionary of Yemeni Arabic, partly collected in Israel is <rs type="bibl" ref="zotid:XEZAEM3H">Piamenta 1991-1992</rs>.</p>
            </div>

      
               </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
