<?xml version="1.0"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="profile_sicily_01">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>A machine-readable profile of Siculo Arabic</title>
        <author xml:id="gunda">Gunda Kinzl</author>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>ACDH-OeAW</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Vienna</pubPlace>
        <date>2021</date>
        <availability status="restricted">
          <p>
            <ref type="license" target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/3.0/"/>
          </p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>This is an original digital text</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <tagsDecl partial="true">
        <rendition xml:id="i" scheme="css">font-style:italics;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="u" scheme="css">text-decoration:underline;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="b" scheme="css">font-weight:bold;</rendition>
      </tagsDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change status="created" when="2019-02-18" who="gunda">created</change>
      <change status="draft" when="2019-02-18" who="#">last modified (revision 4)</change>
      <change status="draft" when="2019-02-18">transformed to TEI-XML</change>
      <change who="#stephan" when="2018-10-03" status="released"/>
    </revisionDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
  <change n="2022-06-20-3-gf63490c" who="GitHub" when="2022-06-23">
add notebook evaluation of the library
   </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div>
        <head>
          <figure>
                <graphic url="sicily_wikimedia.jpg"/>
              <head type="imgCaption" xml:space="preserve">
                <ref target="https://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/commons/thumb/c/c8/Cefalu_BW_2012-10-11_10-50-11.JPG/640px-Cefalu_BW_2012-10-11_10-50-11.JPG">Wikimedia</ref>
               </head>
          </figure>
          <label>Name (English)</label>
          <name type="place" xml:lang="eng">Sicily</name>
          <label>MSA name</label>
          <name xml:lang="ara">صقلية</name>
          <label>MSA name (trans.)</label>
          <name xml:lang="ara-x-DMG">Siqilliyya</name>
        </head>

        <div type="positioning">
         <head>Geo location</head>
          <p>
              <geo>37°37'N 13°56'E</geo>
              <country>Italy</country>
            </p>
        </div>

        <div type="typology">
          <p>West (Maghreb) &gt; Sicily</p>
          <p>Sedentary dialect close to urban Tunisian and Libyan</p>
        </div>

        <div type="general">
          <p>Sicily is the largest island in the Mediterranean sea, separated from 
             mainland Italy by the narrow strait of Messina and only 144 km off 
             the North African coast. Today, apart from Italian, the Italo-Dalmatian 
             Romance language Sicilian is also spoken. </p>
            
          <p>When Sicily was conquered by the Aghlabids in the 9th century, 
              it was inhabited by Roman and Byzantine Christians, and the population
              spoke Greek in the east and a Romance dialect or vulgar Latin in the west. 
              Even before the conquest, Arabic was an important trade language. 
              Immigration by North African arabophone Muslims and Jews as well as 
              Berbers increased and continued when the Fatimids came to power at 
              the beginning of the 10th century. There was never complete Islamization 
              or Arabization of the island, and communities were either arabophone or 
              bilingual; only a few communities in the East remained monolingual Greek 
              speakers throughout.</p>
          <p>The Jewish citizens of Sicily were better acculturated to the predominant 
              Muslim culture and to a higher degree arabicized. The North African Jews 
              were arabophone from the start and the Jewish population spoke Arabic until 
              the end of the 15th century.</p>
          <p>The nominally Fatimid Kalbite dynasty ruled increasingly independently. 
              By the 11th century, their emirate had disintegrated into several 
              principalities. The Normans, who had occupied Southern Italy, gained 
              control over all of Sicily. However, Muslims were not pressured to 
              convert to Christianity, and Latinization was as incomplete as the 
              Arabization was before. In fact, Arab culture blossomed under Norman rule.</p>
          <p>After Muslim revolts in the 13th century, many of them were deported to 
              Lucera in Italy, but at this point, the domination of Arabic and Islam 
              had already long vanished, and several theories exist as to why the Arab 
              communities dissolved so completely and left a comparatively small trace 
              on the Sicilian language as well, among them conversion to Christianity 
              and emigration.</p>
          <p>Sicily shows a magnificent mixture of Hellenic, Byzantine and Islamic art 
              and architecture, as it was a melting pot of cultures and beautifully 
              merged the best of each of them, as can be seen e.g. in the cathedral of 
              Palermo, originally the Grand Mosque. The typical Sicilian cuisine is 
              based on crops introduced by the Arabs, such as sugar cane, pistachios 
              and bitter oranges.</p>
         <p>The Kalbite Emirate of Sicily comprised Malta. The Maltese language developed
             from Arabic, albeit showing strong influence of a Romance superstrate. 
             Some scholars argue that Maltese derived directly from Sicilian Arabic.</p>
        </div>

        <div type="researchHistory">
          <p>Some of our knowledge about Sicilian Arabic stems from <hi rendition="#i">laḥn</hi>-authors who set 
              out to “correct” the dialect spoken by the people in reference to Classical
              Arabic. They viewed the dialect merely as an incorrect rendition of CA, 
              neglecting the diglossic situation. There are also Middle Arabic documents 
              of the Norman period, the so-called <hi rendition="#i">ǧarāˀid</hi>. From toponyms and anthroponyms,
              preserved in Greek and Latin script, conclusions about the vowel system can 
              be drawn.</p>
          <p><rs type="bibl" ref="zotid:ZQ88U7CW">Cusa</rs> published a collection of Sicilian parchments in Arabic and ancient Greek, 
              which has provided ample material for scholars, e.g. <rs type="bibl" ref="zotid:HHGKSCQ8">De Simone’s 1979</rs> work on 
              anthroponyms.</p>

          <p><rs type="bibl" ref="zotid:NMLKNS5Z">Blau 1968</rs> firmly categorises Sicilian Arabic as a Western dialect primarily 
              influenced by North African dialects, although Maltese and Sicilian do show 
              some traits of the Mashriq-dialects.</p>
          <p>Two works by <rs type="bibl" ref="zotid:JI8T4NTP">Pellegrini 1972</rs> and 
            <rs type="bibl" ref="zotid:AKSVPHMH">Caracausi 1983</rs> look at Arabisms in modern 
              Romance languages, particularly Sicilian. Both have also published other 
              works on Arabic in Sicily.</p>
          <p><rs type="bibl" ref="zotid:PP974JDD">Molan’s 1978</rs> dissertation undertakes the reconstruction of Medieval Western 
             dialects through the <hi rendition="#i">laḥn</hi>-literature. A monumental collection is the 
             “Biblioteca Arabo-Sicula” of <rs type="bibl" ref="zotid:38R499WM">Amari 1982</rs>, comprising texts in Arabic that 
             deal with various aspects of Sicilian culture and geography. It is not, 
             however, a collection of Sicilian literary works, but a collection of texts 
             on Sicily in a broader sense.</p>
          <p>Agius has worked extensively on “Siculo-Arabic”, among other topics on the 
              role of the <hi rendition="#i">laḥn</hi>-author Ibn Makkī <rs type="bibl" ref="zotid:EJHJT3CB">(Agius 1994</rs>, 
            <rs type="bibl" ref="zotid:6QKKU653">Agius 1991)</rs>, but also on 
              the adverb <rs type="bibl" ref="zotid:YEES5VQ3">(Agius 1992)</rs>, 
              terminology <rs type="bibl" ref="zotid:Z658B35Q">(Agius 1990</rs>, <rs type="bibl" ref="zotid:GYLM552J">Agius 1987</rs>, 
            <rs type="bibl" ref="zotid:UCCAR7DW">Agius 1986)</rs> 
              and the Siculo-Arabic origin of Maltese. <rs type="bibl" ref="zotid:BE9L54YR">Agius 1996</rs> comprises references 
              to the <hi rendition="#i">laḥn</hi>-literatur, a description of the sociolinguistic situation and 
              deals with Romance and Greek interferences. It is the most comprehensive 
              work on Sicilian Arabic. Agius proposes the development of a pidgin and 
              later creolised Arabic alongside Romance or Greek.</p>
          <p><rs type="bibl" ref="zotid:YV4CZDY9">Borruso 1991</rs> examines Arabic poetry in Sicily, as does 
            <rs type="bibl" ref="zotid:U3GMANW4">Miller 2019</rs> and <rs type="bibl" ref="zotid:QXMC4VJF">2020</rs>, 
              who revises Sicilian Arabic court poetry under Norman rule.</p>
          <p>Although not a work on dialectology, <rs type="bibl" ref="zotid:NN82QKXN">Metcalfe 2014</rs> gives a good overview of 
              the linguistic change from Romance and Greek to Arabic and back to Romance, 
              and he has also written the entry on Sicily in the <rs type="bibl" ref="zotid:3H4YI6QY">EALL</rs>.</p>
        </div>

       
        

        <div type="bibliography">               
                    <p>To view publications on this variety click <rs type="bibl" ref="bibl:reg:Sicily">here</rs>.</p>
                </div>

        

        
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>