<?xml version="1.0"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="profile_shammar_01">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A machine-readable profile of the Bani Shammar tribe</title>
            <author xml:id="gunda">Gunda Kinzl</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>ACDH-OeAW</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna</pubPlace>
            <date>2021</date>
            <availability status="restricted">
               <p>
                  <ref type="license" target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/3.0/"/>
               </p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>This is an original digital text</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <tagsDecl partial="true">
            <rendition xml:id="i" scheme="css">font-style:italics;</rendition>
            <rendition xml:id="u" scheme="css">text-decoration:underline;</rendition>
            <rendition xml:id="b" scheme="css">font-weight:bold;</rendition>
         </tagsDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change status="created" when="2019-12-03T09:44:00Z" who="gunda">created</change>
         <change status="draft" when="2020-03-07T12:46:00Z" who="#">last modified (revision 1)</change>
         <change status="draft" when="2020-09-24T09:36:39.071+02:00">transformed to TEI-XML</change>
         <change when="2020-09-24T09:36:40.018+02:00" status="draft"/>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div>
            <head>
               <figure>
                  <graphic url="#"/>
               </figure>

               <label>Name (English)</label>
               <name type="place" xml:lang="eng">Bani Shammar</name>
               <label>Name (Fuṣḥā, transcription)</label>
               <name xml:lang="ara">Banū Šammar</name>
               <label>Name in local variety (in transcription)</label>
               <name xml:lang="ara-x-DMG">Banī Šammar</name>
               <label>Name (Fuṣḥā, Arabic)</label>
               <name xml:lang="ajp">بنو شمر</name>
            </head>
            <div type="positioning">
                <head>Geo location</head>
                              <p>
                  <geo>27°29'N 41°10'40</geo>
                  <country>Saudi Arabia</country>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="typology">
               <head>Typology (Local)</head>
               <p rend="typology">East (Mashreq) &gt; Arabia &gt; Northern group &gt; Northern Najd</p>
            </div>
            <div type="general">
               <head>General</head>
               <p>The Šammar are one of the largest Bedouin tribal confederations of Arabia. Traditionally, 
                   their lifestyle used to be that of nomadic camel rearers. Most are sedentarized nowadays. 
                   They are located mainly in Saudi-Arabia, Syria and Iraq. According to their oral history, 
                   three of their tribes descend from the Qaḥṭānite Ṭayyiˀ in Yemen (al-Aslam, al-Xrīṣih and 
                   Sinǧārih, the latter two often grouped together as Zūbiʿ), who formed the Šammar section 
                   of Ṭayyiˀ. The fourth tribe, ˁAbdih, also descendants of Qaḥṭān, came to present-day 
                   Saudi Arabia at a later stage and joined the confederation.</p>
               <p>While many settled in Jebel Šammar in northern Arabia, and the oasis city of Ḥā’il, some 
                   migrated north. Of those northern or Mesopotamian Šammar, some became Shiites and there 
                   is also a small Christian minority.  Ḥā’il was an important station for the pilgrims from 
                   Iran and Iraq and the Šammar guaranteed their security and levied fees from the caravans. 
                   Thus, they played a powerful role and the Emirate of the Āl Rašīd was a Šammarī emirate.</p>
               <p>The traditional rivals of the Šammar are the ˁAnaza, and all factions except the al-Aslam 
                   were also in opposition to the Āl Suˁūd and their Wahhabite allies. After the foundation 
                   of Saudi Arabia in 1923, this eventually impeded their employment in lucrative sectors 
                   such as the National Guard forces. The Land Redistribution Act caused the loss of their 
                   tribal <hi rendition="#i">dīra</hi>. Many joined their tribesmen in Iraq, where they still 
                   enjoy a prominent position in society.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="researchHistory">
               <head>Research history</head>
               <p>Ingham, who has conducted much research on the Šammar, states that their dialect is largely 
                   homogenous despite their dispersal over a vast area. Cantineau in two consecutive 
                   articles (<rs type="bibl" ref="zotid:NB2HLKGD">1936</rs> and <rs type="bibl" ref="zotid:TJFGQ7N8">1937</rs>) 
                   explores Bedouin dialects on the Arabian peninsula, preceded by 
                   <rs type="bibl" ref="zotid:PXCFI897">Montagne 1935</rs> on the Šammar of the Ǧazīra in Iraq.</p>
               <p><rs type="bibl" ref="zotid:ZCJGS68X">Abboud 1964</rs> is a dissertation on the dialect spoken 
                   in Ḥā’il, followed by three articles: <rs type="bibl" ref="zotid:PNX637ZB">Abboud 1975</rs> 
                   on verb suffixation, <rs type="bibl" ref="zotid:U267IHY6">Abboud 1978</rs> on the 
                   imperfect prefix and <rs type="bibl" ref="zotid:6KUML942">Abboud 1979</rs> on the verb in general.</p>
               <p>Sowayan, who has worked on oral Bedouin poetry and history, published annotated texts in two 
                   articles (<rs type="bibl" ref="zotid:4GQPSE36">Sowayan 1982a</rs> and <rs type="bibl" ref="zotid:7MEZQUVB">1982b</rs>)
                   and a monograph (<rs type="bibl" ref="zotid:ARXIY97K">Sowayan 1992</rs>), the latter also offering 
                   comments on the grammar of the Šammar dialect, especially syntax.</p>
               <p><rs type="bibl" ref="zotid:Y5WWYMLB">Behnstedt 1997</rs> offers data on the Šammar in Syria, 
                   and also provides a good collection of texts.</p>
               <p>Ingham, whose work on Bedouin dialects and the dialects of the Arabian peninsula is ample, 
                   has treated the Šilgān branch of the Šammar in <rs type="bibl" ref="zotid:NQZK2Z4R">Ingham 1982</rs>. 
                   Virtually all of his works on Najdi Arabic include examples from the Šammari dialect, 
                   such as <rs type="bibl" ref="zotid:QSNSCZY2">Ingham 1994</rs> and 
                   <rs type="bibl" ref="zotid:ELB7YYFT">Ingham 2006</rs>, and most recently 
                   <rs type="bibl" ref="zotid:YKMTMZLX">Ingham 2010</rs>. Ingham also links the fringe 
                   dialect of the Euphrates Bedouins to the Šammar dialect group 
                   <rs type="bibl" ref="zotid:K6NYRV2V">(Ingham 2009)</rs>.</p>
               <p>Recently, three articles discussed the peculiar feminine ending in the Šammari dialect: 
                   <rs type="bibl" ref="zotid:FI4J5FMV">Van Putten 2017</rs>, <rs type="bibl" ref="zotid:UL9VINIK">Procházka 2021</rs> 
                   and <rs type="bibl" ref="zotid:LMULDMWI">Alshammari 2021</rs>.</p>
            </div>

            <div type="dictionaries">
               <head>Dictionaries</head>
               <p><rs type="bibl" ref="zotid:ARXIY97K">Sowayan 1992</rs> includes a 60 page glossary of typical Šammari vocabulary.</p>
            </div>

      <div type="bibliography">
               <p>To view publications on this variety click <rs type="bibl" ref="bibl:geo:Shammar">here</rs>.</p>
            </div>
               </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
