<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Vicav Linguistics</title>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <p>Publication Information</p>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>Information about the source</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div xml:id="vicavLinguistics" xml:space="preserve">
    <head>Linguistics</head>
              
    <p xml:space="preserve">The VICAV Research Environment has been designed 
        as a tool for the presentation of digital material concerning Arabic 
        dialectology. It was intended as a means to promote the efficient 
        exchange of ideas and experiences in an active international community.</p>
              
    <p xml:space="preserve">VICAV serves as an interface between areal and 
        corpus linguistics. The aim is to gather varying digital language 
        resources for a number of different localities. The description 
        of the different varieties hinges on a particular type of text 
        which we call ’language profiles’, concise and standardised 
        ‘form sheets’ that display uniformly arranged information on 
        research history, available literature, salient grammatical 
        features etc. The website will also make accessible bibliographies, 
        dictionaries, glossaries, and different types of transcribed texts.</p>
              
    <p xml:space="preserve">The project proceeds from two basic assumptions: In Arabic
      dialectology, information on new findings and current developments is
      mainly exchanged at international conferences and in scientific
      journals. Due to a steadily increasing number of projects which
      produce digital data too there is an increasing need to make these
      data quickly available to others in the field. There already exist a
      couple of individual webpages which - due to the lack of resources -
      often do not match professional standards. There is a big gap between
      the linguistics communities and Arabic Studies in general and Arabic
      dialectology in particular. Linguistic studies in Arabic dialects have
      widely ignored the works of traditional, i.e. philologically based,
      dialectology and vice versa. We are convinced that VICAV has the
      potential to help to bridge this gap to the benefit of both
      disciplines.</p>
</div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>