<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>VICAV Design Principles</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher ref="https://ror.org/03anc3s24">Austrian Academy of Sciences</publisher>
            <publisher ref="https://ror.org/03prydq77">University of Vienna</publisher>
            <distributor ref="https://ror.org/028bsh698">Austrian Center for Digital Humanities</distributor>
            <date when="2018-09-12"/>
            <address>
               <addrLine>Bäckerstraße 13</addrLine>
               <addrLine>1010 Vienna</addrLine>
               <addrLine>Austria</addrLine>
            </address>
            <availability status="free">
               <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">CC BY 4.0</licence>
            </availability>
            <idno type="VICAVCorpusID">vicavExplBar_DesignPrinciples</idno>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Born digital</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
      <body>
        <head>Design Principles</head>
        <p>Displaying complexly structured scholarly contents on screens has
           always been a design challenge. What has made the situation even more
           complicated is that these days web applications are supposed to run on
           any kind of device. VICAV is basically built on responsive technology.
           However, the website has not been optimised for use on smaller mobile
           devices yet.</p>
        <p>Research environments have to work on the Internet these days, which
           means they need to be implemented as web interfaces that run in browsers.
           By doing this, one forgoes the powerful possibilities of the windows
           based systems, on the other side you attaina higher degree of systemic
           interoperability, reusability and will definitely be able to address a much
           larger audience.</p>
        <p>One drawback of the browser approach has been, that it is usually not
           possible to have several tabs next to each other which hampers any
           processes aiming at comparing texts. Whenever you want to juxtapose
           data one has to find other approaches. One possibility to create a
           flexible solution to the issue of structuring data on a single surface
           has been "panelification", visualising data in smaller units that
           actually emulate forms or windows. We have been experimenting with
           several approaches. In previous versions of VICAV, the panels were
           freely movable on the screen which gave users a lot of flexibility
           to arrange the materials they were interested in on the screen.
           However, experience has shown that the screen tends to
           get cluttered easily.</p>
        <p>The current approach strikes a balance between a structure where
           the user has full control over the psoition and size of panels and
           a static approach where particualr types of text have a fixed position
           on the screen. Most data on the VICAV website is now displayed in
           collapsible panels which have a fixed size and fixed positions.
           Users can open and close these panels, has some control over their
           size and has full control over the order in whcih he accesses
           particular contens. Like this, it is still possible to juxtapose
           particular items and compare them by open them in the right order.</p>
        <p>
           <graphic url="vicav_panels__001.jpg"/>
        </p>
        <p>'Overcrowding' of the screen is avoided by a simple mechanisms that
           collapses panels when there are more than three panels open. The collapsed
           panels still remain on the screen and can be reopened at any time.
           Panels which trigger queries stay open as long as they serve this
           purpose.</p>
        <p>
           <graphic url="vicav_panels__002.jpg"/>
        </p>
        <p>You can open and close any of these panels making use of the controls on the
           purple bar on the left side. The X in the circle closes the panel completely.
           The arrow-dash sign allows to open and close it.</p>
        <p>
           <graphic url="vicav_panel_collapse.jpg"/>
        </p>
        <p>The relativley small display area of the panels can be enlarged by
           clicking on "Expand Panels over Map".</p>
        <p>
           <graphic url="vicav_expand_panels__001.jpg"/>
        </p>
        <p>To make space for new queries you can "Close All Panels".</p>
        <p>
           <graphic url="vicav_close_all_panels__001.jpg"/>
        </p>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
