<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>VICAV Dictionaries</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Information about the source</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
  
</teiHeader>
    
  <text>
      <body>
          <div xml:id="vicavOverview_dictionaries">
              <head>Dictionaries</head>
              
              <p xml:space="preserve">Over the past few years, the number of online Arabic dictionaries has
      soared rapidly. Many websites offering online access to dictionaries
      pursue commercial interests capitalising on easily available data in
      order to create revenues through commercials. Many of these are of
      little use to serious research. Addresses often change which makes it
      impossible to reference them in a persistent manner, the provenance of
      data is in many cases not clear and the quality of information—at
      best—dubious. The following list only contains a chosen few which have
      been arpound for some time already and/or have grown out of research
      projects.</p>
              
              <div>
                  <head>Verbes de l’arabe égyptien: Dictionnaire contextuel raisonné des
                      verbes du dialecte égyptien (parler du Caire)</head>
                  
                  <p xml:space="preserve">This specialised dictionary has been 
        <ref target="http://www.ifao.egnet.net/bases/verbeseg/">online</ref> 
        since 2012.</p>
              </div>
              
              <div>
                  <head>Mawrid Reader: Arabic dictionary interface</head>
                  <p xml:space="preserve">This <ref target="http://ejtaal.net/mr/readme.html">website</ref>
        offers reading access to a number of Arabic dictionaries.</p>
              </div>
              
              <div>
                  <head>Glossarium Græco-Arabicum: A lexicon of the mediæval Arabic
                      translations from the Greek</head>
                  
                  <p xml:space="preserve">The <ref target="http://telota.bbaw.de/glossga/">website</ref> 
          offers access to the files of a lexical project having studied
          the lexicon of mediæval Arabic translations from the Greek.
      </p>
              </div>
              
              <div>
                  <head>Arabic Ontology</head>
                  <p>This a large database, a formal Arabic Wordnet built on the basis of a carefully designed ontology. It is a classification of the meanings of the Arabic terms, based on state-of-art science, rather than on speakers' naïve knowledge. It consists currently of about 1.3K +11K concepts, all mapped to DOLCE, BFO, WordNet, and the Wikidata knowledge graph. </p>
              </div>
              
              <div>
                  <head>Lughatuna: The Living Arabic Project</head>
                  
                  <p xml:space="preserve">This <ref target="http://www.livingarabic.com/about.html">website</ref> 
        offers a dictionary interface. It appears to be the
        work of an enthusiastic hobby lexicographer.</p>
              </div>
              
              <div>
                  <head>Opinion mining for Arabic (OMA)</head>
                  <p xml:space="preserve">The <ref target="http://oma-project.azurewebsites.net/">OMA</ref> project provides a large-scale Arabic Sentiment and Emotion Lexicon and several other related ressources.</p>
              </div>
              
              <div>
                  <head>arabterm - Technical Dictionary</head>
                  <p><ref target="http://www.arabterm.org">arabterm</ref> offers access to a number of special language dictionaries. It is intended as a generally accessible reference for the consistent translation of textbooks, curricula, technical manuals and other specialised texts. The first volume was published in May 2010. The dictionary is joint publication of the Arab League Educational, Cultural and Scientific Organization (ALECSO) and the German Federal Ministry for Economic Cooperation and Development (BMZ).</p>
              </div>
          </div>
      </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
