<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>VICAV Viennese Lexicographic Editor (VLE)</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Information about the source</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   <revisionDesc>
  <change n="2022-06-20-3-gf63490c" who="GitHub" when="2022-06-23">
add notebook evaluation of the library
   </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

   <text>
      <body>
         <div xml:id="vicavOverview_nlp">
            <head>Language Processing Tools</head>

            <p>Meanwhile, there exist numerous tools for processing Arabic language
               data. However, tools that are readily usable and freely available are
               still scarce. </p>

            <div>
               <head>Morphological Analyzers</head>

               <p>Morphlogial processors or taggers assign labels to tokens
                  (wordforms). They can isolate stems, identify word classes (POS=part
                  of speech) or add other morpho-syntactic data to the wordforms.</p>

               <div>
                  <head>Buckwalter Arabic morphological analyzer</head>

                  <p>This has definitely been the most widely applied tool in the
                     field used by at least two generations of computational
                     linguists.</p>
               </div>

               <div>
                  <head>JAVA Arabic Stemmer</head>

                  <p>This programm, also known as <hi rend="italic">Khoja Arabic
                        Stemmer and Tagger</hi>, was written in JAVA and is available
                     from the <ref target="https://sourceforge.net/projects/arabicstemmer/files/">
                        sourceforge</ref> code repository.</p>
               </div>

               <div>
                  <head>ADAM: Analyzer for Dialectal Arabic Morphology</head>

                  <p>
                     <ref target="https://github.com/WaelSalloum/adam">ADAM</ref> is a
                     tool that builds on Buckwalter's analyzer.</p>
               </div>
            </div>

            <div>
               <head>Parsers</head>
               <p>A parser is a tool that performs an automatic analysis of the
                  syntactic structure of digital texts. </p>

               <div>
                  <head>The Stanford Parser</head>

                  <p>It is licensed under a GNU General Public License and comes with
                     extensive support for Arabic.</p>
               </div>
            </div>

            <div>
               <head>Literature</head>

               <div>
                  <head>Introduction to Arabic Natural Language Processing (Synthesis
                     Lectures on Human Language Technologies)</head>

                  <p>To our knowldge, this book by Nizar Y. Habash (Morgan and Claypool
                     2010) is the only monography exclusivly dealing with Arabic NLP.
                     It also comprises a bibliography of relevant other pulications
                     which meanwhile has been outdated by many more publications in
                     the field.</p>
               </div>

               <div>
                  <head>المدونات اللغوية ودورها في معالجة النصوص العربية</head>

                  <p>"Corpora and their Role in Processing Arabic Texts" by
                     <hi rend="italic">Ayman Eddakrouri</hi> was published in
                     2018 and deals with a wide range of digital language ressources.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
         </div>

      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
