<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
             <title>VICAV Corpora (Historical Varieties)</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Information about the source</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   <revisionDesc>
  <change n="2022-06-20-3-gf63490c" who="GitHub" when="2022-06-23">
add notebook evaluation of the library
   </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
          <div xml:id="vicavOverview_corpora_historical_varieties">
              <head>Corpora (Historical Varieties)</head>
              
              <div>
                  <head>Sharing Ancient Wisdoms (SAWS)</head>
                  <p xml:space="preserve">The <ref target="http://www.ancientwisdoms.ac.uk/">SAWS Dynamic
          Library</ref> contains five main groups of texts. Elvira Wakelnig
        and colleagues in Vienna have made available two collections,
        Gnomological Material in Arabic and in Arabic-Spanish transmission,
        and Arabic Philosophical Compendia and Excerpts of Arabic and Latin
        Philosophical Texts; these include, among others, transcriptions of
        two abridgements of the Ṣiwān al-ḥikma, Ps.-ʿĀmirī’s Kitāb
        al-Saʿāda, the first editions of three unpublished Arabic
        compilations of philosophical material, together with further
        excerpts from relevant texts, from Greek sources and from the
        Spanish Bocados di Oro whch drew on this tradition. Apophthegmata et
        gnomae secundum alphabetum comprises the first full edition of an
        important tradition of Greek gnomologia, arranged in alphabetical
        order, and edited from 16 manuscripts by Denis Searby and colleagues
        in Uppsala. A collection of Greek florilegia: Pinakes, prepared by
        Roueché and Searby, presents the tables of contents from three
        previously published Greek gnomologia, to give a further sense of
        the concerns characteristic of such assemblages. Kekaumenos,
        Consilia et Narrationes, is a new edition, by Charlotte Roueché, of
        an 11th century Greek text which is profoundly influenced by the
        tradtion of gnomologia. See a map of the manuscripts which we are
        publishing.</p>
              </div>
              
              <div>
                  <head>A Digital Corpus for Graeco-Arabic Studies</head>
                  
                  <p xml:space="preserve">This <ref target="https://www.graeco-arabic-studies.org">digital
          corpus</ref> assembles a wide range of Greek texts and their
        Arabic counterparts. It also includes a number of Arabic
        commentaries and important secondary sources. The texts in the
        corpus can be consulted individually or side by side with their
        translation. The majority of texts can also be downloaded for
        further analysis. </p>
              </div>
              
              <div>
                  <head>The Quranic Arabic Corpus</head>
                  
                  <p xml:space="preserve">This <ref target="http://corpus.quran.com">corpus</ref> is an 
        annotated linguistic resource which shows the Arabic grammar, 
        syntax and morphology for each word in the text of the Quran. 
        The corpus provides three levels of analysis: morphological annotation, 
        a syntactic treebank and a semantic ontology. The linguistic structure 
        of verses is represented using dependency graphs. The corpus is 
        available under the GNU public license.</p>
              </div>
              
              <div>
                  <head>Digital Archive for the Study of pre-Islamic Arabian
                      Inscriptions (DASI)</head>
                  
                  <p xml:space="preserve">
        <ref target="http://dasi.humnet.unipi.it">DASI</ref> seeks to gather
        all known pre-Islamic Arabian epigraphic material into a
        comprehensive online database, with the aim to make available to
        specialists and to the broader public a wide array of documents
        often underestimated because of their difficulty of access.</p>
                  
                  <p xml:space="preserve">By means of a digitization process through a hybrid data entry/xml
        system developed by the Scuola Normale Superiore di Pisa according
        to international encoding standards, DASI gives access at present to
        more than 7,000 Ancient South Arabian inscriptions recorded by the
        University of Pisa team under the direction of Alessandra Avanzini.
        Thanks to the fruitful collaboration with other two major European
        centres for the study of the epigraphic documentation of the Arabian
        Peninsula, also sections of the two corpora of Ancient North Arabian
        inscriptions (supervision by Michael C.A. Macdonald, University of
        Oxford) and Aramaic inscriptions (supervision by Laila Nehmé, UMR
        8167, CNRS-Paris) are being prepared for consultation.</p>
              </div>
              
              <div>
                  <head>The Arabic Papyrology Database (APD)</head>
                  
                  <p xml:space="preserve">
        <ref target="http://www.apd.gwi.uni-muenchen.de:8080/apd/project.jsp">APD</ref> is a tool enabling you to access the editions of Arabic
        documents written on different material such as papyrus, parchment
        or paper. Those productive editions are an often unraised treasure
        for almost every aspect of Islamic history up to the 16th c.
        A.D.</p>
              </div>
              
              <div>
                  <head>Analytical Database of Arabic Poetry</head>
                  
                  <p xml:space="preserve">The <ref target="https://arts.st-andrews.ac.uk/arsem/project/">
        project</ref> aims at documenting the transmission of early
        Arabic poetry. The database represents a contribution to European
        research on the Arabic language and the Arabic philological
        heritage, which so far lacks even such fundamental tools as an
        etymological dictionary of the Arabic language or a complete
        dictionary of Classical Arabic.</p>
              </div>
              
              <div>
                  <head>The Princeton Geniza Project</head>
                  
                  <p xml:space="preserve">The <ref target="https://geniza.princeton.edu/pgp/">Princeton
        Geniza Project</ref> is a searchable database of documentary
        Geniza texts. The corpus currently consists of 4,320 transcriptions
        in Judaeo-Arabic, Hebrew, Aramaic and Arabic. </p>
              </div>
              
              <div>
                  <head>Perseus Digital Library</head>
                  
                  <p xml:space="preserve">The Perseus Digital Library, the central hub for digital language
        ressources in the Latin and Ancient Greek languages, also contains
        historical <ref target="http://www.perseus.tufts.edu/hopper/collection?collection=Perseus:collection:Arabic">Arabic language documents</ref>.</p>
              </div>
              
              <div>
                  <head>Islamic Law Materialized</head>
                  
                  <p xml:space="preserve">This <ref target="http://cald.irht.cnrs.fr/php/ilm.php">corpus</ref> 
        contains primary sources for Islamic law and legal
        practice in pre-modern Muslim societies. The online presentation is
        the first ever collection of scattered editions of legal documents
        from the 2nd/8th to the 9th/15th century, often with improved
        readings compared to earlier print versions. Documents are presented
        with the Arabic text in modern spelling and with full
        bibliographical data.</p>
              </div>
              
              <div>
                  <head>Thesaurus d'épigraphie islamique</head>
                  
                  <p xml:space="preserve">This <ref target="http://www.apd.gwi.uni-muenchen.de:8080/apd/links.jsp">website</ref> is accessible to registered users only.</p>
              </div>
          </div>
          
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
