<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Title</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Information about the source</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div xml:id="vicavTypesOfText">
            <head>Types of Text/Data</head>
            <p>Apart from its linguistic goals, the project has been pursuing strong
               interests in various aspects of text technology. The output of the
               work of the contributors is published in form of different types of
               digital language ressources. Our research interests in this
               respect have been related to issues of digital lexicography, visualisation
               of digital language resources in a multilingual environment and the
               application of standards and de-facto standards.</p>

            <div>
               <head>Language Profiles</head>
               <p>At the heart of the website, there are what we have called language
                  profiles. This type of text consist in short sketches of varieties
                  of spoken contemporary Arabic. The intention has been to proceed
                  in a complementary manner to similar endeavours (such as EALL). For the
                  time being, we do not plan to give detailed grammatical descriptions
                  but rather focus on general information, research histories and
                  available literature.</p>
            </div>

            <div>
               <head>Dictionaries</head>
               <p>We have been working on several digital dictionaries which have
                  been created as part of different projects. We call them dictionaries
                  (and not glossaries) as they are made up of self-contained entries
                  which are not only used as glosses. All of these have been created to be used
                  as part of language teaching activities.</p>
            </div>

            <div>
               <head>Bibliography</head>
               <p>The bibliography is an ongoing effort. Given the limited
                  resources at our disposal, it can not be exhaustive. Here again,
                  one of our intentions is to provide the community with readily reusable
                  standardised material.</p>
            </div>

            <div>
               <head>Standards</head>
               <p>An important part of our work is standards and de-facto standards.
                  The most important part of this toolbox are the
                  <ref target="http://www.tei-c.org/Guidelines/P5/">Guidelines of the
                     Text Encoding Initiative (P5)</ref>. All digital language
                  resources used in this application have been encoded in accordance
                  with TEI (P5).</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <!-- End of vicavTypesOfText -->
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
