<?xml version="1.0"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>VICAV NEWS</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Information about the source</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   
</teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>     <div xml:id="vicavNews">
            <head type="newsHeader">News</head>

            <div type="newsItem">
               <p><hi rendition="#b">3.-5.9.2025:</hi> The <ref target="https://wibarab.acdh.oeaw.ac.at/">WIBARAB</ref> project hosts the
                  <hi rendition="#i">Arabic Linguistics Forum</hi> conference at the University of Vienna.</p>
            </div>
         
         <div type="newsItem">
               <p><hi rendition="#b">Spring 2025:</hi> The new <ref target="https://tunocent.acdh.oeaw.ac.at">TUNOCENT Website</ref> gets launched.</p>
            </div>
         
           <div type="newsItem">
               <p><hi rendition="#b">3.-4.10.2024:</hi> The <ref target="https://wibarab.acdh.oeaw.ac.at/">WIBARAB</ref> project hosts its second Symposium titled
                  <hi rendition="#i">Interdisciplinary Perspectives on the 'Tribe' in the WANA Region</hi>.
                  Here, scholars from different disciplines such as history, (socio-)linguistics and social 
                  anthropology come together to discuss different aspects of the concept of 'tribe' and its many interpretations in different 
                  academic fields and thus contributing to the project's theoretical framework.</p>
            </div>
         
          <div type="newsItem">
               <p><hi rendition="#b">30.9.2024:</hi> The <ref target="https://tunocent.acdh.oeaw.ac.at">TUNOCENT</ref> project ends. After more than five years of intensive work, 
               the results of the project are considerable: The TUNOCENt dataset now contains 71 profiles, 195 feature lists, 185 sample texts and 24 corpus texts. In addition, 
               the metadata of all 2683 recordings can be browsed through.</p>
            </div>
         
          <div type="newsItem">
               <p><hi rendition="#b">23.7.2024:</hi>The ACDH hosts a meeting dedicated to digital lexicography: 
                  Members of the <ref target="https://de.dariah.eu/">DARIAH</ref> Working Group on Lexical 
                  Resources and ACDH team members disuss various topics concerning TEI Lex-0. This is highly relevant
                  for the VICAV dictionaries: the <ref target="https://www.oeaw.ac.at/acdh/research/linguistics/research/corpus-linguistics/shawi-the-shawi-type-arabic-dialects">SHAWI</ref> 
                  dictionary is being encoded according to the Lex-0 specifications and it is planned to convert 
                  the other VIVACV dictionaries into Lex-0 in the future. Another topic that was discussed in this meeting 
                  are the finer points of the encoding of language varieties. Given that the language profiles are a vital part of the platform, this topic is of particular importance for 
                  VICAV, and the results of this discusseion might shape the VICAV profiles in the future. </p>
            </div>
         
          <div type="newsItem">
               <p><hi rendition="#b">1.12.2023:</hi> Laurent Romary, Director of Scientific Culture and Information at INRIA, visits Vienna again to join the 
                  <ref target="https://wibarab.acdh.oeaw.ac.at/">WIBARAB</ref> team in discussions about the progress of the WIBARAB database and the setting-up of the project's digital text corpus.</p>
            </div>
         
          <div type="newsItem">
               <p><hi rendition="#b">7.-9.6.2023:</hi> The <ref target="https://wibarab.acdh.oeaw.ac.at/">WIBARAB</ref> project hosts its first Symposium titled
                  <hi rendition="#i">New Data and Fresh Perspectives</hi>.
                  In three days, the team members present and discuss with the guests the project's ongoing work,preliminary results, and methodological and 
                  theoretical considerations.</p>
            </div>
         
           <div type="newsItem">
               <p><hi rendition="#b">February-March 2023:</hi> Two more fieldwork campaigns are conducted by members of the <ref target="https://wibarab.acdh.oeaw.ac.at/">WIBARAB</ref> project take place.
               team. This time, the destinations are Jordan and Sudan.</p>
            </div>
         
         
         <div type="newsItem">
               <p><hi rendition="#b">20.5.2022:</hi> The Director of Scientific Culture and Information at INRIA, 
                  Laurent Romary, comes to Vienna to intensively discuss <ref target="https://wibarab.acdh.oeaw.ac.at/">WIBARAB</ref>'s TEI based linguistic database with the project team.
               Consequently, the database's data model is based on the results of this meeting.</p>
            </div>
         
           <div type="newsItem">
               <p><hi rendition="#b">January-May 2022:</hi> The first fieldwork campaigns of the <ref target="https://wibarab.acdh.oeaw.ac.at/">WIBARAB</ref> project take place.
               Members of the team go to Jordan, Saudi Arabia, Kuwait, Morocco, and Lebanon to collect data which will ultimately feed the <ref target="https://wibarab.acdh.oeaw.ac.at/">WIBARAB</ref>
                  database and form a text corpus.</p>
            </div>
         
         <div type="newsItem">
               <p><hi rendition="#b">1.10.2021:</hi> The <ref target="https://wibarab.acdh.oeaw.ac.at/">WIBARAB</ref> project starts. WIBARAB <hi rendition="#i">(What is Bedouin-Type Arabic?)</hi> 
                  is funded by an ERC Advanced Grant (101020127-WIRARAB) and investigates the linguistic and socio-historical realities behind the millennia-old dichotomous concept of nomadic and 
                  sedentary people in the Middle East and North Africa. It will run for five years and will expand the VICAV infrastructure. A vital part of the WIBARAB project will be its linguistic 
                  database that will incorporate both previously published and newly gathered data on more than 300 Arabic varieties.</p>
            </div>
         
         <div type="newsItem">
               <p><hi rendition="#b">2.6.2021:</hi> With 20 new profiles there are now 106 profiles. </p>
            </div>
         
          <div type="newsItem">
               <p><hi rendition="#b">1.2.2021:</hi> The <ref target="https://www.oeaw.ac.at/acdh/research/linguistics/research/corpus-linguistics/shawi-the-shawi-type-arabic-dialects">SHAWI</ref> project starts
                  The project is funded by the Austrian Science fund (FWF, P-33574), and investigates the Arabic dialects of the so-called Shawi-type, wihich are spoken by small cattle breeding Bedouin tribes 
                  in regions of Turkey, Syria and Iraq. The SHAWI project builds on the VICAV infrastructure and will add to VICAV a sixth dictionary as well as a comparatively large corpus.</p>
            </div>


            <div type="newsItem">
               <p><hi rendition="#b">27.1.2021:</hi> Entirely revamped VICAV 3.0 goes public. The bibliography has now 4722 entries!</p>
            </div>

            <div type="newsItem">
               <p><hi rendition="#b">19.12.2020:</hi> The Baghdad dictionary has now over 1100 entries.</p>
            </div>

           
            <div type="newsItem">
               <p><hi rendition="#b">5.4.2019:</hi> Bettina Leitner has contributed a new feature list for <ref target="feature:ling_features_ahwaz/Ahwaz">Ahwaz (Iran)</ref>.</p>
            </div>

            <div type="newsItem">
               <p><hi rendition="#b">1.4.2019:</hi> The <ref target="https://tunocent.acdh.oeaw.ac.at">TUNOCENT</ref>
               project starts. TUNOCENT (=Tunisia’s Linguistic terra incognita) investigates the
               Arabic varieties of northwestern and central Tunisia. It will run for
               four years and builds on the VICAV infrastructure.
               </p>
            </div>

            <div type="newsItem"><p><hi rendition="#b">18.3.2019:</hi> Our bibliography has just gone beyond the 4000 entries mark. The 4028 bibliographic items contain 6304 geo-tags and 13.045 taxonomy labels.</p></div>

            <div type="newsItem">
               <p>
                  <hi rendition="#b">15.3.2019:</hi> New function to <rs ref="text:vicavExploreFeatures">compare features</rs>.</p>
            </div>

            <div type="newsItem">
               <p>
                  <hi rendition="#b">1.3.2019:</hi> The <rs ref="text:dictFrontPage_Baghdad">Baghdad dictionary</rs> goes online.</p>
            </div>

            <div type="newsItem">
               <p><hi rendition="#b">28.2.2019:</hi> VICAV has 41 new profiles, all in
                  all <rs ref="text:vicavExplanationProfiles func:insertProfileMarkers()">58 profiles </rs> now!</p>
            </div>

            <div type="newsItem">
               <p><hi rendition="#b">2.2.2019:</hi> The <rs ref="text:vicavExplanationBibliography">VICAV
                     Bibliography</rs> has undergone a substantial rebuild. All the bibliographical data is now also encoded in TEI
                  (P5), all the VICAV data now being available in TEI.
               </p>
            </div>

            <div type="newsItem">
               <p><hi rendition="#b">3.12.2018:</hi> The cross <rs ref="func:createNewCrossDictQueryPanel()">dictionary search</rs> is finished.
                  It is now possible to query all dictionaries simultaneously.
               </p>
            </div>

            <div type="newsItem">
               <p><hi rendition="#b">31.12.2016:</hi> The <ref target="https://tunico.acdh.oeaw.ac.at/">TUNICO</ref> project ends.</p>
            </div>

            <div type="newsItem">
               <p><hi rendition="#b">1.8.2013:</hi> The <ref target="https://www.oeaw.ac.at/acdh/projects/completed-projects/tunico">TUNICO</ref> project starts.</p>
            </div>

         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
