<?xml version="1.0"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>VICAV Overview Spoken Arabic Corpora</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Information about the source</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>

   </teiHeader>

   <text>
      <body>
         <div xml:id="vicavOverview_corpora_spoken">
            <head>Resources for Spoken Varieties</head>

            <p>The number of digitally encoded Arabic language corpora has been on
               the rise in recent years. The following list is an attempt at listing
               some that are relevant to linguistic research and is by no means meant
               to be exhaustive. Please let us know about missing items.</p>

            <div>
               <head>CorpAfroAs</head>
               <p>
                  The <ref target="http://corpafroas.huma-num.fr">Corpus for Afroasiatic Languages (CorpAfroAs)</ref>
                  began as an integrated pilot project, producing transcribed and sound-indexed
                  spoken data. The varieties included in the corpus were Moroccan Arabic,
                  Tripolitanian Arabic (Libya) and Juba-Arabic (Sudan). The transcribed 
                  texts encompass both narratives and conversations, are text-sound 
                  aligned using Praat and ELAN software, and annotated for prosody 
                  and morphosyntax. The Arabic data comprises approximately 25,000 words. 
                  The project set an excellent example for then best practices. On their website,
                  you can find extensive information on how to build corpora of
                  spoken language. The data is freely available.</p>
            </div>

            <div>
               <head>Multi-Arabic Dialect Applications and Resources corpus (MADAR)</head>

               <p>MADAR consists of 2,000 parallel sentences translated into the
                  dialects of 25 Arab cities. It was developed through a three-year
                  international collaboration involving researchers from Gulf universities
                  and Columbia University. The source sentences were originally from
                  the <hi rend="italic">Basic Traveling Expression Corpus (BTEC)</hi> in
                  both French and English. The dataset is freely accessible and
                  organized by city, with each version presented as tab-separated
                  values in Arabic script without diacritics. Although it's highly
                  beneficial for many natural language processing tasks, its usefulness
                  for traditional dialectology is limited due to the absence of phonetic
                  details and sufficient metadata. It is available through various websites, also through the
                  <ref target="https://archive.org/details/madar-dialectical-corpus-all-by-w">Internet Archive</ref>.</p>
            </div>

            <div>
               <head>CORVAM Speech corpus of Maghrebi varieties</head>
               <p>CORVAM is a tool for the study of Arabic and
                  Berber varieties in the Maghreb in terms of teaching and research
                  and for the preservation of language and culture in the Maghreb. The
                  corpus is a result of the research team <hi rend="italic">nhəḍṛu.
                     Dialectología y sociolingüística del Magreb</hi>, and has been
                  conducted at the University of Zaragoza with the participation of
                  members from other universities and research institutes both from
                  Spain and abroad. The project was developed under the lead
                  of <ref target="bibl:Vicente">Ángeles Vicente</ref> and the <ref target="http://corvam.unizar.es/en/">website</ref>
                  is being hosted by the University of Zaragoza.</p>
            </div>

            <div>
               <head>TUNICO</head>
               <p>In contrast to the corpora mentioned above,
                  <ref target="https://tunico.acdh.oeaw.ac.at/about_corpus.html">TUNICO</ref> represents
                  the language of a single location, the Tunisian capital. It
                  comprises transcriptions of over 30 hours of dialogues and
                  narrative interviews, collected in 2013 in Tunis. One of the
                  project’s stated goals was to record speakers from diverse
                  social backgrounds, all under the age of thirty-five, who
                  have grown up and still reside in the Greater Tunis area. The
                  project team attempted to realise a balanced gender ratio.
                  The project, titled <hi rend="italic">Lexical Dynamics in the
                     Greater Tunis Area: a Corpus-Based Approach (TUNICO)</hi>,
                  ran from August 2013 until July 2016 and was the first of
                  the VICAV projects. The data is partially annotated with
                  lemmas and word-class information through
                  several semi-automatic steps using the dictionary. Unlike
                  other dialectological projects, TUNICO aimed to capture contemporary
                  language and the speech of the younger generation, primarily
                  high school or university students.</p>
            </div>


            <div>
               <head>Tunisian Arabic Corpus (TAC)</head>
               <p>This is a comparatively large corpus of Tunisian Arabic mainly
                  collected from the Internet. The texts are supposed to represent spoken
                  Arabic presented in Arabic script. According to the creators, TAC
                  currently approximately 1 million words. <ref target="http://tunisiya.org">The
                     website (http://www.tunisiya.org/)</ref> was last updated with
                  a new interface in January 2025.</p>
               <p>The provided metadata gives author, a date and a rough
                  categorisation of the texts, including folklore, poetry, popular song
                  lyrics, collections of proverbs, and screenplays for movies,
                  television shows and plays. </p>
            </div>

            <div>
               <head>Corpus of Moroccan Arabic Writers of Short Stories and Literary
                  Reviews</head>
               <p>Information on this corpus in Arabic script can be found
                  <ref target="http://www.ugr.es/~dgb/corpus/">here</ref>.</p>
            </div>

            <div>
               <head>In their own voices, in their own words: A
                  sociolinguistically-informed corpus of Nigerian Arabic</head>

               <p>This corpus created by Jonathan Owens who has
                  published extensively about <ref target="bibl:reg:Nigeria">Nigerian
                     Arabic</ref> represents dialects spoken on the periphery of
                  the Arabic-speaking world. Over time, the texts have been
                  available at various URLs in recent years (most recently at
                  <ref target="https://www.arabistik.uni-bayreuth.de/de/forschung/ehemalige-forschungsprojekte/index.html">https://www.arabistik.uni-bayreuth.de/de/forschung/ehemalige-forschungsprojekte/index.html</ref>) and
                  are made up of recorded and transcribed group conversations and interviews. </p>
            </div>

            <div>
               <head>Curras: Corpus for Palestinian Arabic</head>
               <p>This collection of 60k words consists in texts collected from Facebook,
                  Twitter, "Watan Aa Water" scripts, and others. Every word in the
                  corpus was manually annotated with a set of metadata attributes
                  to describe the orthographical, morphological, and semantic features
                  of the word such as part of speech, prefixes, stem, suffixes, dialect
                  lemma, MSA lemma, surface, gender, number, mode, and a gloss in English.
                  It is available as part of the <ref target="https://sina.birzeit.edu/currasat/search.html">SinaLab
                     corpora</ref>, of Birzeit University.</p>
            </div>

            <div>
               <head>Gulf Arabic Corpus (Gumar)</head>
               <p>Gumar was created as part of the Computational Approaches to
                  Modeling Languages CAMeL lab in New York University Abu Dhabi NYUAD. The corpus contains a unique genre of
                  written material, anonymous publicly published long conversational
                  novels. It contains texts from Bahrain, the Emarates, Kuwait, Oman,
                  Qatar and Saudi-Arabia. It was also morphologically annotated,
                  contains more than 112 million words in over 1,200 documents
                  and can be searched <ref target="https://camel.abudhabi.nyu.edu/gumar/">online</ref>.</p>
            </div>

            <div>
               <head>Dialects of Arabic </head>

               <p><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Yaron_Matras">Yaron Matras’</ref>
                  <hi rend="italic">Dialects of Arabic</hi> project was carried out at the University of Manchester
                  between 2015-2020 and was created through interviews conducted with informants
                  from Algeria, Egypt, Iran, Iraq, Jordan, Kuwait,
                  Lebanon, Morocco, Oman, Palestine, Saudi Arabia, Sudan and Syria.
                  Since the recent disappearance of the website the data has remained
                  accessible as a spreadsheet via the <ref target="https://www.kratylos.org">Kratylos
                     repository</ref>.</p>
            </div>

            <div>
               <head>Arabic Dialects Dataset</head>
               <p>This <ref target="http://www.lancaster.ac.uk/staff/elhaj/corpora.htm">collection</ref>
                  is one of several corpora being provided by Mahmoud El-Haj
                  (Lancaster University). It consists in transcriptions of Arabic
                  script of Gulf, Egypt, Levantine and Tunisian Arabic dialects in
                  addition to MSA.</p>
            </div>

            <div>
               <head>Arabic Speech Corpus</head>
               <p>The <ref target="http://en.arabicspeechcorpus.com/">Arabic Speech
                     Corpus</ref> was developed by Nawar Halabi at the University of
                  Southampton. It was recorded in south Levantine Arabic (Damascian
                  accent) using a professional studio. Synthesized speech as an output
                  using this corpus has produced a high quality, natural voice. It is
                  released here under a non-commercial creative commons license.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
