<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
             <title>VICAV Corpora (Modern Written Language)</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Information about the source</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   
</teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
          <div xml:id="vicavOverview_corpora_msa">
              <head>Corpora (Modern Written Language)</head>
              
              <p xml:space="preserve">The number of corpora of Modern Standard Arabic have been on the rise
    over the past two decades. Still, the number of readily available 
    material is rather limited.</p>
              
              <div>
                  <head>KALIMAT Multipurpose Arabic Corpus</head>
                  
                  <p xml:space="preserve">KALIMAT is an Arabic natural language resource that consists of 
        Arabic articles collected from the Omani newspaper Alwatan. It was prepared 
        by Mahmoud El-Haj (Lancaster University). Articles in the collection 
        fall into six categories: culture, economy, local-news, international-news, 
        religion, and sports. KALIMAT is freely available via 
        <ref target="https://sourceforge.net/projects/kalimat/files/?source=navbar">sourceforge.net</ref>.</p>
              </div>
              
              <div>
                  <head>International Corpus of Arabic (ICA)</head>
                  
                  <p xml:space="preserve">The <ref target="http://www.bibalex.org/ica/en/About.aspx">International 
        Corpus of Arabic (ICA)</ref> is an ambitious attempt to
        build a representative corpus of the Arabic language as it is used
        all over the Arab world, with the aim of supporting research on such
        language. The ICA is planned to contain 100 million words. Once
        finished, the analyzed version will be the first analyzed Arabic
        corpus available as a linguistic resource for researchers. It is
        also the first systematic investigation of national varieties within
        the Arabic speaking community, this should prove very useful for
        linguists who believe that their theories and descriptions of
        language should be based on real, rather than contrived, data."</p>
              </div>
              
              <div>
                  <head>arabiCorpus</head>
                  
                  <p xml:space="preserve">
        <ref target="http://arabicorpus.byu.edu/">This corpus</ref> is a
        sizeable corpus (173,600,000 words) containing texts in five main
        categories or genres: Newspapers, Modern Literature, Nonfiction,
        Egyptian Colloquial, and Premodern. It has been maintained by Dil
        Parkinson, professor of Arabic and allows users to find larger
        structures and grammatical patterns through frequency analysis,
        regular expression searching, and other interface features.</p>
              </div>
              
              <div>
                  <head>Wortschatz Universität Leipzig</head>
                  
                  <p xml:space="preserve">This <ref target="http://wortschatz.uni-leipzig.de/de">website</ref> offers
        access to large amounts of data crawled form the Internet. There is
        also Arabic data available. The data is unstructured, search results
        come with little metadata. However, the results are enriched with
        cooccurrences which makes it a verz interesting tool both for
        learners and lexicographers.</p>
              </div>
              
              <div>
                  <head>King Abdulaziz City for Science and Technology (KACST) Arabic corpus</head>
                  
                  <p xml:space="preserve">The KACST Arabic corpus is claimed to be a carefully sampled corpus the 
         contents of which are classified based on time, region, medium, domain and 
         topic. It comprises more than 700 million words from the pre-Islamic era 
         to the present day (a period covering more than 1,500 years). However, most 
         of the data belongs into the recent past which is why it is listed under MSA. 
         It can be explored on the <ref target="http://corpus.kacst.edu.sa/">Internet</ref> using a variety of tools.</p>
              </div>
              
              <div>
                  <head>Sketch Engine Corpora</head>
                  
                  <p xml:space="preserve">Sketch Engine is a corpus manager and text analysis software that
        has been developed by Lexical Computing Limited since 2003. It
        allows to analyse large amounts of textual data and is primarily
        used by lexicographers and linguists. Sketch Engine also provides
        corpora in currently 90+ languages. There are several 
        <ref target="https://www.sketchengine.co.uk/user-guide/user-manual/corpora/by-language/arabic-text-corpora/"> 
        Arabic corpora</ref> available which come as part of the regular
        payable subscription.</p>
              </div>
              
              <div>
                  <head>WebCorp Live</head>
                  
                  <p xml:space="preserve">The <ref target="http://www.webcorp.org.uk">website</ref> offers a suite of 
         tools which allows direct access to the World Wide Web as a corpus.</p>
              </div>
              
              <div>
                  <head>Leeds Arabic Corpora</head>
                  
                  <p xml:space="preserve">Serge Sharoff's <ref target="http://corpus.leeds.ac.uk/query-ar.html">interface</ref> 
         allows to search several corpora. The list
         contains an Arabic Internet corpus, Al-Hayat News corpus (1999-2001),
         an Arabic Wikipedia from 2008, a Computer Science corpus and others.</p>
              </div>
              
              <div>
                  <head>Arabic Concordancer</head>
                  
                  <p xml:space="preserve">AC is an <ref target="http://efolio.iium.edu.my/arabicconcordancer">interface</ref> 
         to a corpus published by the International Islamic University 
         of Malaysia. The corpus itself is not available. On the website 
         it says that it contains 14 million Arabic words taken from various 
         academic resources such as theses, journal articles, conferences 
         papers etc.</p>
              </div>
          </div>
          
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
