<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:space="preserve">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>VICAV Dictionaries</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Information about the source</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div xml:id="vicavDictionariesTechnicalities">
            <head>Dictionaries</head>
            <div>
               <head>Data</head>

               <p>All entries in the dictionaries which are not further indicated are
                  taken from data provided by the collaborator(s) cited on the front
                  page of each dictionary. Data extracted from other published sources
                  is indicated as such and includes the respective reference.</p>
            </div>

            <div>
               <head>Encoding</head>

               <p>For a detailed desciption of the encoding applied on this website <ref target="text:vicavDictionaryEncoding">click here</ref>.</p>
            </div>


            <div>
               <head>Arabic roots</head>

               <p>In order to facilitate cross-dialectal comparative search all word
                  roots are have to be taken as being strictly etymological, i.e. they
                  reflect the corresponding roots of Standard Arabic wherever
                  possible. The source of reference is the Dictionary of Modern
                  Written Arabic by Hans Wehr (English version edited by J. Milton
                  Cowell, Wiesbaden: Harrassowitz, 1979). For words which have entered
                  Arabic from other languages a (in many hypothetical) root consisting
                  of the mere consonantal structure of the word in question is
                  given.</p>
            </div>

            <div>
               <head>Part-of-speech</head>

               <p>As for verbs a subcategory indicating the so-called verbal form is
                  provided (using the traditional order labelled by Roman numerals
                  from I to X, in case of quadriliteral roots Iq and IIq).</p>

               <p>In many cases a clear distinction between adjective and active or
                  passive participle is not possible. If a given lemma is mainly used
                  in an adjectival sense it is labelled as such but with an additional
                  category that indicates the word is morphologically seen a
                  participle.</p>

               <p>The gender of Arabic nouns is not noted unless it is contradictory
                  to the rules of Arabic morphology (which is particularly the case
                  with unmarked feminine nouns).</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <!-- End of vicavDictionaries -->
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>