<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title>VICAV Viennese Lexicographic Editor (VLE)</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<p>Publication Information</p>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<p>Information about the source</p>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
	
</teiHeader>
	<text>
		<body>
			<div xml:id="vicavVLE">
				<head>Viennese Lexicographic Editor (VLE)</head>
				<p>VLE is a fairly new piece of software that first came into existence
    as a by-product of an entirely different development activity: the
    creation of an interactive online learning system for university
    students. Thus, it was first used in a collaborative glossary editing
    project carried out as part of university language courses at the
    University of Vienna. As the tool proved to be flexible and adaptable
    enough, it was also put to work in other projects. The interface is
    built around an XML editor. The communication between the dictionary
    client and the server has been implemented as a RESTful web
    service.</p>
				<p>The interface is built around an XML editor that allows to process
    standard-based lexicographic and terminological data, basically any
    XML-based format such as LMF, TBX, RDF, or TEI can be handled. The
    program provides a number of useful functions to automate editing
    procedures. It can check the structural integrity (well-formedness) of
    input on the fly. Technologically, it draws not only on the XML core
    specification but also on several cognate technologies. XSLT and XPath
    play an important role both for visualizing and modifying existing
    datasets. Lexicographers can insert elements on the basis of
    predefined XML Schemas. Most of the functions can be applied both to
    single and multiple lemmas. One of the most recent improvements is a
    versioning system and an improved working mode that allows
    lexicographers to work on the XML data without actually seeing the
    tags. Furthermore, the editor also has a configurable interface
    enabling lexicographers to access external corpora and to integrate
    example sentences from them into dictionary entries. The communication
    between the dictionary client and the server has been implemented as a
    RESTful web service.</p>
			</div>
		</body>
	</text>
</TEI>
