<?xml version="1.0"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>VICAV Overview Spoken Arabic Corpora</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Information about the source</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   
</teiHeader>

   <text>
      <body>
         <div xml:id="vicavOverview_corpora_spoken">
            <head>Resources for Spoken Varieties</head>
            <p>The number of digitally encoded Arabic language corpora has been on
               the rise in recent years. The following list is an attempt at listing
               those that are relevant to linguistic research and is by no means meant
               to be exhaustive. Please let us know about missing items.</p>
            <div>
               <head>CorpAfroAs</head>
               <p>CorpAfroAs was an integrated pilot project that also produced Arabic
                  data. On the <ref target="http://corpafroas.huma-num.fr">project web
                     site</ref>, you can find extensive information on how to build
                  corpora of spoken language. The data is available.</p>
            </div>
            <div>
               <head>CORVAM Speech corpus of Maghrebi varieties</head>
               <p>This very recent development is a tool for the study of Arabic and
                  Berber varieties in the Maghreb in terms of teaching and research
                  and for the preservation of language and culture in the Maghreb. The
                  corpus is a result of the research team <hi rend="italic">nhəḍṛu.
                     Dialectología y sociolingüística del Magreb</hi>, and has been
                  conducted at the University of Zaragoza with the participation of
                  members from other universities and research institutes both from
                  Spain and abroad. The project has been been developed under the lead
                  of <ref target="bibl:Vicente">Ángeles Vicente</ref> and the <ref target="http://corvam.unizar.es/en/">website</ref>
                  is being hosted by the University of Zaragoza.</p>
            </div>
            <div>
               <head>TUNICO</head>
               <p>The <ref target="https://tunico.acdh.oeaw.ac.at/about_corpus.html">TUNICO
                     Corpus</ref> was created as part of the project <hi rend="italic">
                     Linguistic dynamics in the Greater Tunis Area: a corpus-based
                     approach</hi> which ran from August 2013 until July 2016. TUNICO grew
                  as a satellite project out of the VICAV project.</p>
            </div>
            <div>
               <head>Tunisian Arabic Corpus</head>
               <p>This is a comparatively large corpus of Tunisian Arabic mainly
                  collected from the Internet. The corpus has a very nice
                  <ref target="http://tunisiya.org">web interface</ref>.</p>
            </div>
            <div>
               <head>Corpus of Moroccan Arabic Writers of Short Stories and Literary
                  Reviews</head>
               <p>Information on this corpus can be found
                  <ref target="http://www.ugr.es/~dgb/corpus/">here</ref>.</p>
            </div>
            <div>
               <head>In their own voices, in their own words: A
                  sociolinguistically-informed corpus of Nigerian Arabic</head>
               <p>This <ref target="http://www.neu.uni-bayreuth.de/de/Uni_Bayreuth/Fakultaeten/4_Sprach_und_Literaturwissenschaft/islamwissenschaft/arabistik/en/Idiomaticity__lexical_realignment__and_semantic_change_in_spoken_arabic/Nigerian_Arabic/index.html"/>corpus which is hosted by the university of Bayreuth has been
                  created by <ref target="bibl:Owens">Jonathan Owens</ref> who has
                  also published extensively about <ref target="bibl:reg:Nigeria">Nigerian
                     Arabic</ref>.</p>
            </div>
            <div>
               <head>Curras: Corpus for Palestinian Arabic</head>
               <p>This corpus of 60k words consists in texts collected from Facebook, Twitter, "Watan Aa Water" scripts, and others. Every word in the corpus was manually annotated with a set of metadata attributes to describe the orthographical, morphological, and semantic features of the word such as part of speech, prefixes, stem, suffixes, dialect lemma, MSA lemma, surface, gender, number, mode, and a gloss in English. </p>
            </div>
            <div>
               <head>Gumar Corpus</head>
               <p> The <ref target="https://camel.abudhabi.nyu.edu/gumar/">Gulf
                     Arabic Corpus</ref> (Gumar) was created as part of the
                  Computational Approaches to Modeling Languages CAMeL lab in New York
                  University Abu Dhabi NYUAD. The corpus contains a unique genre of
                  written material, anonymous publicly published long conversational
                  novels. A a huge collection of these novels was found online in one
                  place. 1,200 MS Word documents were automatically downloaded. </p>
            </div>
            <div>
               <head>Database of Arabic Dialects</head>
               <p>The <ref target="http://www.arabic.humanities.manchester.ac.uk/database-of-arabic-dialects/">Database of Arabic Dialects</ref> was created through interviews conducted with informants
                  from Algeria, Egypt, Iran, Iraq, Jordan, Kuwait,
                  Lebanon, Morocco, Oman, Palestine, Saudi Arabia, Sudan and Syria. On the basis
                  of a quite exhaustive questionnaire, the website allows to explore linguistic
                  phenomena and to compare a wide range of dialects. The project was set up and organised
                  by <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Yaron_Matras">Yaron Matras</ref> at the University of Manchester.
               </p>
            </div>
            <div>
               <head>Arabic Dialects Dataset</head>
               <p>This <ref target="http://www.lancaster.ac.uk/staff/elhaj/corpora.htm">collection</ref>
                  is one of several corpora being provided by Mahmoud El-Haj
                  (Lancaster University). It consists in transcriptions of Arabic
                  script of Gulf, Egypt, Levantine and Tunisian Arabic dialects in
                  addition to MSA.</p>
            </div>
            <div>
               <head>Arabic Speech Corpus</head>
               <p>The <ref target="http://en.arabicspeechcorpus.com/">Arabic Speech
                     Corpus</ref> was developed by Nawar Halabi at the University of
                  Southampton. It was recorded in south Levantine Arabic (Damascian
                  accent) using a professional studio. Synthesized speech as an output
                  using this corpus has produced a high quality, natural voice. It is
                  released here under a non-commercial creative commons license.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
